<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A complete history of the late revolution from the first rise of it to this present time in three parts ... : to which is added a postscript, by way of seasonable advice to the Jacobite party.</title>
            <author>Miege, Guy, 1644-1718?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18999</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12284475</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12284475</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58818</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58818)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 871:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A complete history of the late revolution from the first rise of it to this present time in three parts ... : to which is added a postscript, by way of seasonable advice to the Jacobite party.</title>
                  <author>Miege, Guy, 1644-1718?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Clement ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Guy Miege. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. The growth of popery in England, under the reign of the late King Charles, by his connivence, French intrigues, &amp;c. -- II. Our imminent ruin in his popish successor King James his reign, by his invading of our laws, religion, and liberties. With a particular and impartial narrative of the fictitous Great Belly -- III. Our wonderful and happy deliverance, by the Prince of Orange, our present King's famous expedition over into England. With an account of the late King James's desertion and abdication of Their Majesties happy succession to the throne of Great Britain, and of their prosperous reign hitherto, by defeating the Jacobites dark plots in England, by suppressing their open rebellion in Scotland, and by the total reduction of Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lancashire Plot, 1689-1694.</term>
               <term>Jacobites.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58818:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58818:1"/>
            <p>A COMPLETE HISTORY Of the LATE REVOLUTION, FROM The firſt Riſe of it to this preſent Time.</p>
            <p>In Three Parts.</p>
            <list>
               <head>SHEWING</head>
               <item>I. The Growth of Popery in <hi>England,</hi> under the Reign of the late King <hi>CHARLES;</hi> By his Connivence, <hi>French</hi> Intrigues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. Our Imminent Ruin in his Popiſh Succeſſor King <hi>JAMES</hi> his Reign; By his Invading of our Laws, Religion, and Liberties. With a Particular and Impartial Narrative of the fictitious <hi>Great Belly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. Our Wonderful and Happy Deliverance, by the <hi>PRINCE</hi> of <hi>ORANGE,</hi> Our preſent King's famous Expedition over into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> With an Account of the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Deſertion and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, of Their Majeſties happy Succeſſion to the Throne of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of Their proſperous Reign hitherto, by Defeating the <hi>Jacobites</hi> dark Plots in <hi>England,</hi> by Suppreſſing their open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and by the Total Reduction of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To Which is Added A Poſtſcript, by way of Seaſonable Advice to the <hi>Jacobite</hi> Party.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Clement</hi> at the <hi>Lute</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:58818:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58818:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY Of the LATE REVOLUTION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>PART I.</hi> Shewing the Growth of Popery in <hi>England,</hi> under the Reign of the late King <hi>Charles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO demonſtrate the Growth of Popery in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as the firſt Occaſion of all our late Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I ſhall begin at the Head, and come up to the Original Cauſe.</p>
               <p>All the World knows, that the Ruin of the Proteſtants, and the Inſlaving all <hi>Europe,</hi> have been the two grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV; the firſt influenced by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed blind Zeal, and the laſt being the product of his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable and boundleſs Ambition. To the firſt he was prompted by thoſe Spiritual Engineers, the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who ever made it their buſineſs to ſet the World in a Combuſtion. And the laſt he attempted, to pleaſe his own Humour, and gratifie his exceſſive Pride.</p>
               <p>The Holy Cabal had reſolv'd upon the Extirpation of the Proteſtant Hereſie. And ſuch has been the effect of their Inchanting Eloquence, and reputed Skill in Politicks, that they are in a manner become Companions for Princes and Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heads of the Roman Communion.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58818:3"/>
               <p>In point of Conſcience they are their uſual Directors, and their Deciſions are to them as Laws and Oracles. 'Tis there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no wonder that the <hi>French</hi> King, being inſpirited by theſe Men, ſhould follow their Directions. Whoſe Confeſſors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Order always indulged him in his Criminal Courſes, with Aſſurances of Salvation, if he did but apply himſelf with Zeal and Fervency to ſo meritorious a Work as the Extinguiſhing the Proteſtant Hereſie. This forſooth would make him the Favourite of Heaven, and an Immortal Prince on Earth.</p>
               <p>Infatuated with theſe Deluſions he ſtruck in with the Society, ſubſcribed to their Dictates, and reſolved upon their Project. In ſhort, he diſpos'd all things to purchaſe Heaven with a Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Zeal, and to improve his Fame upon Earth with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Character of a Tyrant and Perſecutor. His Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Subjects, to whom he owed his Elevation on the Throne, he undermined during ſeveral years, and by degrees weakened their Party, till he thought fit at laſt to pull off the Mask, and to fall foul upon them.</p>
               <p>Abroad he had his Agents to inſpire other Princes with the ſame Unchriſtian Zeal, and put them upon the ſame Methods of Cruelty, for promoting of a Religion whoſe Principles chiefly tend to make the Clergy Great and the Laity Slaves. <hi>Hungary, Bohemia, Poland,</hi> and <hi>Piemont</hi> not long ſince, have felt the fury of this Spirit of Perſecution. And <hi>England</hi> by his means was like, but few years ago, to feel the ſame Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo near it was to fall a Sacrifice to the ambitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Popery, and with its fall to carry the Ruin of all the Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Deſign was laid in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> is apparent by the Growth of Popery here, whilſt he ſwayed the Scepter. And for this we may thank our unhappy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Wars in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. when that good King being put to death by a prevailing Party, and the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Family diſperſed thereupon into Popiſh Countries, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Royal Blood were eaſily poyſoned with Popiſh Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations, that the only Way for their Reſtauration, and to Reign Arbitrarily, was to imbrace, or at leaſt to favour the Roman Religion.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58818:3"/>
               <p>Tho' I am not fully ſatisfyed, that King <hi>Charles</hi> II. was ever actually<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Reconciled to the Roman Church, (whatever has been reported to the contrary) but rather that he was too clear-ſighted to think well of her Principles; yet it is plain, by the whole Series of his Reign, that he made his Government as eaſy and favourable to the Roman Party as his Circumſtances would allow, and that he gave 'em all poſſible Incouragement. But, as he was a Prince naturally inclined to Clemency, and abhorrent from Cruelty; ſo this Proceeding of his was rather look'd upon as an Effect of his good Nature, than of any Deſign upon the Proteſtant Intereſt of theſe Kingdoms. If we reflect u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Courſe of his Life during his Reign, it ſeems his Aim was to pleaſe all Parties, that he might injoy himſelf, and Reign in Quietneſs. But ſtill he kept to an outward Profeſſion of the Reformed Religion, as by Law eſtabliſhed, and from time to time ſoothed up his Parliaments with ſolemn Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his faithfulneſs to their Religion and Liberties.</p>
               <p>Such was the Poſture of Affairs in his Reign, that tho' he would not himſelf bring in Popery downright, yet he made the way ſmooth for it. For, whilſt he minded his Amours more than the Government, the Thieves ſtole in, and grew upon us. Who being countenanced by his Brother the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> a Prince more daring and gone over to the Roman Church, began now to build all their Hopes upon him.</p>
               <p>The King having no Iſſue by the Queen, and in proceſs of time no hopes of any by her, the Duke remained the Heir ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, and was conſequently lookt upon as the Riſing Sun. On whom His Majeſty, too much given to Eaſe and Pleaſure, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdened himſelf of the active and troubleſom part of the Government, which he left in a great meaſure to his Care. Thus his <hi>R. H.</hi> had a fair Opportunity to gratifie the <hi>Roman</hi> Party, and improve their Intereſt here, whilſt the King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And, tho' <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e did not openly profeſs himſelf a Papiſt, his forſaking at laſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> wherein he was bred and born, and eſpouſing ſo much as he did the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Intereſt, ſufficiently evidenced his being of that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>The King being a Prince bigotted to no Religion, but link<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, gave him a great Latitude. And this was ſo far improv'd by the <hi>French</hi> King, that in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58818:4"/>which happened at <hi>Dover Anno</hi> 1670 between our King, his Brother, and their Siſter the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> a Treaty was there managed by the Dutcheſs between both Kings, whereby the <hi>French</hi> King did promiſe King <hi>Charles</hi> to <hi>Subject</hi> his Parliament <hi>to him, and to Eſtabliſh the</hi> Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <hi>in his Kingdom.</hi> In order to which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> muſt firſt be brought down, and both Kings joyn in Arms to make them incapable of being any longer a Support or Refuge for Proteſtants. <hi>Delenda eſt Carthago.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, <hi>Anno</hi> 72, the Storm broke out upon <hi>Holland,</hi> that Neſt of Hereticks. And in two Campaigns we ſaw that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent State, at that time our only Rival upon the Ocean, brought by the <hi>French</hi> King's Land Forces to the laſt Extremity; whilſt we haraſſed them at Sea, and fought them, but without any great Advantage on our ſide. We had indeed a <hi>Frenchy</hi> Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron in conjunction with our Fleet, but their buſineſs (it ſeems) was not to fight. All their Care was to be Spectators of our Fights at a convenient diſtance, and to ſee if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did their Duty well. In the mean time they learnt the Art of our Sea-fights, and had the ſatisfaction to ſee theſe two Proteſtant Nations thus weaken one another, which was the <hi>French</hi> King's chief Aim.</p>
               <p>This Conduct of the <hi>French</hi> at Sea, with the amazing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of their Arms by Land, happened to open our Eyes. For till then we were poſſeſſed of the Juſtice of the War on our ſide, conſidering the many Provocations of the States, as they were muſtered in the King's Declaration. We could not imagine, that King <hi>Charles</hi> had any other Deſign than to curb their Pride, and leſſen their Power at Sea, for the benefit of our Trade and Navigation; in order to which a little help, tho' from <hi>France,</hi> was not thought amiſs. The <hi>Dover-Treaty</hi> lay then under the <hi>Roſe,</hi> and we knew not what Snake lay in the Graſs.</p>
               <p>The King, wanting Mony to proſecute the War, convened his Parliament. The Danger we were in by the apparent Ruin of a Neighbouring State of the ſame Religion with us, and now become (with our help) a Prey to the <hi>French,</hi> came ſoon under Debate. The Parliament voted a Peace with the <hi>States.</hi> And the King, finding no Mony was to be had without it, yielded to their Deſire, and made a ſeparate Peace. This <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58818:4"/>ſtartled King <hi>Lewis;</hi> who from this very time concluded, that King <hi>Charles</hi> was not to be relyed on for the execution of that grand Religious Deſign he had been ſo long big with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. And, to be even with him for his Deſertion in this War, he cauſed not long after the <hi>Dover</hi> Treaty to be publiſhed with his Priviledge, by the Abbot <hi>Primi,</hi> in his Hiſtory of the War with <hi>Holland;</hi> whereby he chiefly deſigned to make the King odious to his People.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>York</hi> upon this was look'd upon as the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Perſon for the Project in hand, who wanting neither Zeal nor Ambition, was a Veſſel altogether prepared and mould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his purpoſe. Whereas King <hi>Charles</hi> was like the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> neither Cold nor Hot, and therefore to be ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out.</p>
               <p>The Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> or rather the <hi>French</hi> King by her means, had ſent to King <hi>Charles</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Curtain Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but a true Member of the Holy Church, as a Pledge (or Memorandum) of the <hi>Dover</hi> Treaty. Who, for her cloſe and faithful Commerce with the King, was made <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>P.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame Care he took of his <hi>R. H.</hi> to keep him in a right Cue, and ſteady to his Principles; but by way of Marriage. So that he was both Procurer, and Match-maker. The Match was <hi>Mary</hi> the late Duke of <hi>Modena</hi>'s Daughter, an <hi>Italian</hi> Princeſs of no great Fortune, but of an Ancient Family, and (which was moſt to the purpoſe) a Princeſs intirely devoted to the preſent Intereſt.</p>
               <p>The Duke had been three Years and a half a Widower. And, as the Caſe ſtood, there was a Neceſſity for his <hi>R. H.</hi> to venture on a ſecond Match, that the Succeſſion to the Crown might be Intailed either by Nature or Art to an Heir Male. The Lady <hi>Mary</hi> and the Lady <hi>Ann,</hi> his two Daughters by <hi>Ann</hi> his firſt Wife, were bred and born Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and ſuch were not for the preſent Turn.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Charles,</hi> who was ſenſible how unacceptable this Match was to his People, and fearing ſome ill Conſequences of it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, reſolved however to diſpoſe of his Royal Nieces, and to Marry them to Proteſtant Princes, to allay the Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and Fears from this New Match. Which indeed were ſomething the leſs, for the then common Opinion, That His Royal Highneſs was too much <hi>Frenchifi'd</hi> to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58818:5"/>get any durable I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue. To the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> was given in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to the Prince of <hi>Orange, Anno</hi> 1677; and the Lady <hi>Ann</hi> to Prince <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> in the Year
1683.</p>
               <p>But, few days after the Lady <hi>MARY</hi> was married to the Prince of <hi>ORANGE,</hi> the Dutcheſs of <hi>YORK</hi> was brought to bed of a <hi>Son,</hi> created Duke of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> who dying in four or five days, the <hi>Popiſh Faction</hi> had but a ſhort Joy of it.</p>
               <p>In the mean time his R. H. being the next Heir to the Crown, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> reſolved not to loſe this Opportunity, turned every <hi>Stone</hi> to make their Party good, by <hi>Plotting</hi> and <hi>Conſpiring</hi> even with Authority againſt the Government. The KING was healthful, and of a ſtrong conſtitution, but wanted zeal or boldneſs to ſecure their Intereſt. The DUKE was zealous and bold, but wanted a ſound Body. In ſhort, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all humane probability, the KING by the ſtrength of Nature was the moſt likely to live.</p>
               <p>Theſe Conſiderations were like enough to give Birth to that famous <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> which upon its breaking out made ſo great a Noiſe in the World, I mean the <hi>Popiſh Plot.</hi> And, tho I cannot believe it in all its Branches, as made out by Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> yet in the main 'tis more than probable, that there was a <hi>Plot</hi> on foot againſt the Government.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> the Dukes Secretary's, intercepted Letters, are a ſufficient Proof of this; who kept, as appears by thoſe <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> a cloſe Correſpondence with Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> (the <hi>French</hi> King's Confeſſor) for the <hi>Extirpating the Proteſtant Religion in theſe Kingdoms,</hi> under the name of the <hi>Northern Hereſy.</hi> That <hi>to Extirpate</hi> imports a violent Act, is a thing undeniable. So that the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion was not to come in by fair means, or by way of perſuaſion, but by force and violence. And 'tis like a great deal more of that wicked <hi>Deſign</hi> had appeared, if amongſt <hi>Coleman's</hi> lateſt Letters for two years and a half that were brought to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> many had not been there ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, and kept from the ſight of the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Yet, upon his <hi>Trial,</hi> he openly avowed the Deſign of <hi>Subverting the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> wherein he owned himſelf a ſubordinate Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Plot</hi> kept for a while the <hi>Papiſts</hi> under Hatches, and forced the <hi>Duke</hi> himſelf (upon the <hi>King's</hi> Command) to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw for ſome time out of the Kingdom; ſo that he went firſt <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58818:5"/>to <hi>Flanders,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>Scotland.</hi> Mean while the Houſe of Commons, who lookt upon him as the great Abettor and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter of the <hi>Popiſh Intereſt,</hi> went ſo far as to attempt his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> from the Crown<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But, as vigorouſly as it was carried on in the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> it was quaſhed in the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> by the <hi>Church of England</hi> Party, which ſtood ſtifly for the Succeſſion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Tide</hi> now began to turn, and the <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> to have a fair Proſpect. The <hi>Duke</hi> was called home; and His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty disbanded <hi>Parliament</hi> after <hi>Parliament,</hi> in hopes to get a healing one. But, failing thereof, he publiſhed a plauſible <hi>Declaration</hi> touching the Cauſes that moved him to Diſſolve the two laſt Parliaments. Which, being read in all Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Chappels, did very much ſtrengthen the <hi>Court Party,</hi> and turned the Hearts of many People againſt the late <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> as having over-ſhort the Mark.</p>
               <p>Which <hi>Houſe,</hi> conſiſting moſt of <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> gave a Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy to the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> and indeed to all the <hi>Church-Party,</hi> that under colour of rooting out <hi>Popery,</hi> they deſign'd nothing leſs than the Ruin of the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſo to kill two Birds with one Stone. The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> on the other ſide, ſeeing the <hi>Church Party</hi> ſo ſtiff for the <hi>Dukes Right</hi> to the Succeſſion, tho upon the Grounds of Juſtice and Equity, fail'd not to clamour againſt them as Abettors of <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> in Maſcarade. In ſhort, the Fewd grew ſo great between both Parties, row diſtinguiſhed by the Nicknames of <hi>TORIES</hi> and <hi>WHIGS,</hi> that, had not his Majeſty (who now beſtirred himſelf in theſe difficult Times) prevented it by his great Care and Wiſdem, it had certainly broke out into a Flame.</p>
               <p>In the mean time theſe unhappy <hi>Differences</hi> gave fair play to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who know beſt how to fiſh in troubled Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> grew now out of date, and loſt much of its Credit. Then up ſtarts another, called the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Plot,</hi> which proved fatal to ſeveral Perſons of Quality, and others of a lower Rank. The King, now exaſperated in the higheſt degree againſt the <hi>Diſſenting Party,</hi> ordered the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> to be put in execution, which made the Breach ſo much the wider betwixt Them and the Church Party. And, whilſt the poor <hi>Diſſenters</hi> lay under the laſh, an offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58818:6"/>ſort of <hi>Church of England</hi> Miniſters made it their buſineſs to preach the ſtupid Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> with as much Zeal and Fervency as if there had been no Salvation without it. Which ſome were hired for with a Promiſe of Church-Preferment, whilſt others did it meerly to ſhew their Parts; but all wonderfully to the purpoſe of the <hi>Roman Catholick Party,</hi> and to help forward the Deſigns of the next Reign. The City of <hi>London,</hi> which had ſtrongly appeared againſt the <hi>Dukes</hi> Intereſt, was now called to an Account, and a Writ of <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> (a dreadful piece of Latin, before which no Reaſon could ſtand) iſſued out againſt them, to take away their Charter; which was accordingly done. Then other Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations were prevailed upon fairly to ſurrender their <hi>Charters,</hi> in expectation of new ones, whereby all their Magiſtrates and Officers were dependant upon the King's Will. And, by the <hi>Duke's</hi> Intereſt, many falſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were got into Places of Truſt, who upon the puſh would be ready to join with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and lend them their helping hands.</p>
               <p>Thus all Things were finely prepared againſt his Majeſties <hi>Exit,</hi> to make room for his Brother. And, which is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, at the very time when the King was reſolved to ſift out ſome Miſcarriages, and much inclined to call a new Parliament, an <hi>odd kind of Fit</hi> ſeiz'd upon him, which in four days time bereav'd him of his Life and Crown.</p>
               <p>Thus died King <hi>Charles,</hi> a Prince who was neither a ſound <hi>Papiſt,</hi> nor a zealous <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Admired for his great Saga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, beloved for his Clemency, and the fitteſt Prince in the World to Reign, had not his over-Indulgence to Eaſe and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures made him averſe from Buſineſs. In which unhappy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per he was too much followed by his Subjects of both Sexes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58818:6"/>
               <head>THE HISTORY Of the LATE REVOLUTION.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>PART II.</hi> Shewing Our Imminent Ruin in the Reign of the late King <hi>James;</hi> With an Account of the ſuppos'd Great Belly.</head>
               <p>KING <hi>Charles</hi> being dead (the Lord knows how) ſome wept upon his Tomb for Joy, but moſt for Sorrow. The <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> were the moſt concerned in the firſt, and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (whatever he was) in the laſt. We were but threatned before with the <hi>Danger</hi> of a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſion,</hi> now we had it. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> had a bleſſed (but doubtful) proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of it, and now they were in poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>To Secure which, the Blood of the deceaſed King was hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chilled in his Veins, when his next Succeſſor <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> was Proclaimed King at <hi>White-hall</hi> and in the City, in great haſte, that no Man might pretend Ignorance. So that King <hi>Charles</hi> was ſcarce gone off the Stage, when his <hi>Brother,</hi> to play the laſt Act, enters, and aſcends the Throne.</p>
               <p>No <hi>Prince</hi> more courteous, more obliging, or more promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at firſt, than he was to his new Subjects, but particularly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58818:7"/>to the <hi>Church of England</hi> Party. He came in like a <hi>Lamb,</hi> but reigned like a <hi>Lion,</hi> and followed in all things the Steps of King <hi>Lewis.</hi> Not but that he had innate Vertues of his own, but none that could ſtand proof againſt the precipitate Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of the <hi>Roman Clergy,</hi> and the irreſiſtible Influence of thoſe hot-brain'd States-men the <hi>Jeſuites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So great was the Opinion of his Juſtice and Valour, when Duke of <hi>York,</hi> that many <hi>Proteſtants</hi> durſt rely upon his Juſtice, and moſt promiſed themſelves great Matters from his Valour. Eſpecially when, upon his Acceſſion to the Crown, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Council, that he would protect and favour the <hi>Church of England,</hi> for her unſhaken Loyalty; and to his Parliament, that he would carry the Glory of <hi>England</hi> beyond all his Predeceſſors.</p>
               <p>Upon theſe Aſſurances he allayed for ſome time the Fears of his Proteſtant Subjects, but eſpecially the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> which thereupon Addreſſed him from all Parts of the Kingdom, as their <hi>Tutelar Angel.</hi> In ſhort, ſo great on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den were the Hopes of this King, that <hi>Edward</hi> III, and <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> V. the moſt glorious Monarchs of <hi>England,</hi> were like upon his Account to be hiſſed out of our <hi>Engliſh Chronicles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it was not long before he pulled off the Mask. And firſt to gratifie the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Party, he declar'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of their Communion, and made open Profeſſion of it. Which ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi> lookt upon as a good Omen, and the product of a generous Soul above Diſſimulation; whilſt others more clear-ſighted lookt upon it as an effect of a wilful Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that thought it needleſs to Diſſemble, now the Power was in his own hands.</p>
               <p>To Eſtabliſh his Religion here was, I confeſs, a difficult Task, conſidering how ſmall the <hi>Popiſh Party</hi> was, the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> then (by the beſt Computation) being reckon'd 200 to one. But the Advantage of a Crown is a great Bait, and has a mighty Influence. The Hopes of worldly Preferment, and the Dread of Majeſty, would in all probability draw in a great Party. Beſides what was expected, by way of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, from the Induſtry and Activity of <hi>Popiſh Emiſſaries.</hi> Nor do I doubt, but the <hi>King</hi> promiſed himſelf great Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the <hi>Church of England</hi> Party, which having ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58818:7"/>ſo much to ſecure his Succeſſion, would not (as he thought) recoil, and leave him now in the lurch, who ſo lately had made unto them new Proteſtations of his particular Favour and Protection. The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were then under the laſh of the Law, and not without ſome apprehenſion of the <hi>French.</hi> Thus, with this proſpect of Things, the King fell preſently to work, by feeling firſt under-hand the <hi>Pulſe</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> in Credit and Authority amongſt his Proteſtant Subjects.</p>
               <p>But, whilſt he was taken up with theſe gentle Motions, a Storm was raiſed all of a ſudden in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the late Earl of <hi>Argile;</hi> and at the ſame time another in the Weſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth.</hi> Who both appeared in Arms with their Parties in their ſeveral Stations; but ſo unſucceſsfully, that, after the loſs of many Mens Lives in the Field, they loſt their own upon the Scaffold. Theſe two Rebellions, which ſtartled ſo much the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Party, till they ſaw the Iſſue of it, gave them a great Advantage, and raiſed their Expectations of Succeſs to an Infallibility. The <hi>King</hi> had now a great Army on foot. And tho the VVork was done for which the ſame was raiſed, yet he would not part with it; but kept it ſtill on foot, contrary to Law, for his further Deſigns, and to keep the Nation in aw.</p>
               <p>For the Preſervation of our Laws, Religion, and Liberties, it was provided by the Wiſdom of our Parliaments, upon the Growth of <hi>Popery</hi> in the late King's Reign, That all Perſons appointed to bear any Office in Church or State ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves to be not <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by taking the Oaths of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and receive thereupon the <hi>Sacrament</hi> according to the <hi>Church of England.</hi> But, upon the Raiſing of the foreſaid Army, the King was pleaſed to protect againſt thoſe Laws many <hi>Popiſh Officers</hi> that ſerved in the Army, without taking the <hi>Oaths.</hi> And in his <hi>Speech</hi> to both <hi>Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> on the 9th of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1685, he told the Parliament in plain words, <hi>That, though the ſaid Officers were not Qualified according to the late Teſts for their Employments, yet he would neither expoſe them to Diſgrace, nor himſelf to the Want of them.</hi> And, tho the <hi>Parliament</hi> did highly except againſt it, as an open Violation of thoſe Laws which were our main Bulwark againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> yet his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58818:8"/>would by no means recede from his Word. A Debate was held to diſpence thoſe Unqualified Officers then act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ally in Service with the Fenalty of the Law, provided no more were admitted. But this would not ſerve the King's turn. Who, to prevent any further Heats about it, prorogued the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll <hi>Feb.</hi> 10 following; and ſo put it off by further Pror<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gations, till it was at laſt Diſſolved.</p>
               <p>Mean whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, he made it his buſineſs to New-model his dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved Army, now conſecrated to more pious I ſes, and kept on foot to accompliſh the great Work of reſturing <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> Both Officers and Soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iers were Reformed, and ſuch of both ſorts put in as would incourage and promote the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o loſe no Time, whole Sholes of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> with Multitudes of <hi>Lay-Papiſts,</hi> came over daily from <hi>France,</hi> and other <hi>Parts,</hi> as often as the Wind would permit; ſome to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert us, and others to Cut our Throats. The firſt, like the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> came over by Sea and Land to make <hi>Proſelytes;</hi> and liked <hi>England</hi> ſo well, that they ſtuck to it like <hi>Burr.</hi> Whilſt poor <hi>Lapland,</hi> and other wretched Countries, are left to their Temporal and Spiritual Darkneſs, ſeldom viſited by thoſe Lights of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi> And firſt, to take off from our Minds the frightful Notions we had of <hi>Popery,</hi> they laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the old way of <hi>Controverſies</hi> from <hi>Scripture, Tradition,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and ſo new-vamped their <hi>Roman</hi> Tenets, after the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> late invented Dreſs, that it was hard to diſcern at firſt view the <hi>Popiſh</hi> from the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> Such was their Reſemblance, that it was <hi>Alter Ego.</hi> But the Cheat was quickly found out, and hiſſed at here, by all Men of Reaſon and Underſtanding. Then was held a Diſputation at <hi>White hall</hi> in the King's Preſence, wherein his Party came off ſo ſhamefully, that his Majeſty was fain to excuſe their Weakneſs, by ſaying, <hi>That a good Cauſe might be baffled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet, notwithſtanding theſe Repulſes, the <hi>Popiſh Emiſſaries</hi> having now (contrary to Law) the liberty of the <hi>Preſs,</hi> ply'd it hard to get Proſelytes, but ſtill with little Succeſs. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence had ſo ordered it, that the <hi>Church of England</hi> was never ſtocked with ſo many Sound, Pious, and Learned <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58818:8"/>as we had in this Juncture. So that this Spiritual War, begun by <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> ended to their Confuſion. The <hi>Church of England</hi> bore the brunt of it all, and the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> would not meddle, for fear of giving Offence; nor was there any need of it.</p>
               <p>The King found by this time how little was to be expected from <hi>Roman Emiſſaries,</hi> and that Compulſion at laſt muſt do the Work. <hi>France</hi> ſhewed him the Way, where the holy Deſign was now ripe for Execution, without any fear of a Check from <hi>England.</hi> For now King <hi>Lewis</hi> fairly pulled off the Mask, and by his Edicts <hi>Anno</hi>
1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>85. told the World in plain terms, that his Deſign of Reconciling his <hi>Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> to the <hi>Holy Church</hi> was from his Coming to the Crown, that all his former Edicts in their behalf, his Acknowledging and Regiſtring in Parliament their great Services to the <hi>Crown,</hi> and his Advancement of many of them to the higheſt Dignities Civil and Military, were but ſo many Blinds to cover his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign (for which he calls God to witneſs) to aboliſh their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by degrees. And, to ſhew what Opinion he had of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> he declared them Incapable to claim the benefit of <hi>Treaties, Promiſes,</hi> or <hi>Oaths,</hi> made to them by the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to theſe his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian Principles,</hi> he broke the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ties of <hi>Religious Oaths,</hi> by Revoking his <hi>Proteſtant Subjects</hi> grand <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>Priviledges,</hi> the famous Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> which from its very Foundation was counted Irrevocable; and by forcing his <hi>Religion</hi> upon them, through the miraculous Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his <hi>Apoſtolick Dragoons.</hi> Who ('tis true) had no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to take away their Lives, but all the Comforts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by Want and barbarous Uſage, Spoiling and Plundering, dark Priſons and loathſom Dung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, by parting the Husband and Wife, and robbing Parents of their deareſt Children.</p>
               <p>But, leſt the VVorld ſhould think, that the <hi>French</hi> King's Zeal was confined within the Bounds of his Dominions, he loſt no Opportunity to make it known, that his Deſign was againſt the whole Body of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and firſt againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> whoſe Converſion would much facilitate that of other <hi>Proteſtant Nations.</hi> This appears by that noted Speech made to him at <hi>Verſailles</hi> in the Year 1685. by a <hi>French</hi> Biſhop, in <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58818:9"/>the Name of the whole Clergy of <hi>France.</hi> VVherein the Biſhop, having magnified the King for his Zeal in Suppreſſing the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in his Kingdom, tells him, that <hi>England</hi> offered to his Majeſty one of the moſt glorious Occaſions that he could wiſh for, and that his <hi>Britiſh</hi> Majeſty wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his Protection and the Support of his Arms to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the <hi>Catholick Religion</hi> in his Dominions. This Speech was publiſhed by the <hi>French</hi> King's Authority, and the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it ſuffered to come over freely into <hi>England.</hi> VVhich lookt ſomething odd, and beneath a King of <hi>England,</hi> to be thus expos'd to the VVorld as a Prince to come under the Protection of a King of <hi>France;</hi> over whoſe Kings, and Kingdom, his Anceſtors had ſo often Triumphed. But nothing (it ſeems) was to be thought Inglorious, that might ſerve the <hi>Popiſh Deſign</hi> of Rooting out the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such was King <hi>James</hi> his Zeal for <hi>Mother Church,</hi> that (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Father <hi>Peter</hi>'s Relation) his Majeſty told him in his Chamber, That he had rather Reign but one Year to an end, tho in Troubles, and die with the Converſion of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> than to Reign proſperouſly 30 years, and leave them in <hi>Hereſy,</hi> as he ſound them at his Acceſſion to the Crown. A Zeal in ſome ſenſe like that of <hi>Moſes;</hi> who, to ſave the People under his Government, was willing to be blotted out of the <hi>Book of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this Saying, and his Proceedings, with the <hi>French</hi> King's Aſſiſtance, we may gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs what he intended for us. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert us, he went about to ſubvert the Laws; and, to make us good Chriſtians after his own Way, he made his Will the meaſure of his Government, without any regard to his Oaths and Promiſes, to Juſtice or Equity.</p>
               <p>However, to colour what he did with ſome ſhew of Juſtice, he ſet up a new Claim, a Thing called the <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> unknown to former Ages, and now ſuddenly ſtarted up as a Branch forſooth of the King's Prerogative. By which means he threw aſide thoſe two great Stumbling-Blocks, the Penal Laws &amp; the Teſts, being all our legal Securities for the Preſervation of our Religion and Liberties; and ſo ſhook the very Foundation thereof, that we had no Security leſt againſt his Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58818:9"/>
               <p>'Tis not denyed, that, in the Caſes of Treaſon and Felony, the King of <hi>England</hi> may, by vertue of his Prerogative, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Puniſhment that a Tranſgreſſor has incurred. But it cannot be with any colour of Reaſon inferred from thence, that the King can intirely-ſuſpend the Execution of thoſe Laws relating to Treaſon or Felony; unleſs it is pretended, that he is Cloathed with a Deſpotick and Arbitrary Power. And, as no Laws can be made but by the joint Concurrence of King and Parliament; ſo likewiſe Laws ſo Enacted, which ſecure the publick Peace and ſafety of the Nation, and the Lives and Liberties of every Subject in it, cannot be Repealed or Suſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by the ſame Authority.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, the Judges declared this <hi>Diſpenſing Power</hi> to be a Right belonging to the Crown. But, before that pernicious Judgment could be obtained, firſt the Opinion of the Judges was privately examined. Such of them as could not in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence concur in ſo pernicious a Sentence were turned out, and others ſubſtituted, till by the Changes which were made in the Courts of Judicature that Judgment was at laſt obtained, to give ſome Credit to the Cauſe. And, amongſt thoſe that were raiſed to theſe Truſts, ſome were profeſſed Papiſts, and conſequently Incapable of all ſuch Imployments. However it does not appear, how it is in the Power of the Twelve Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to offer up the Laws, Rights, and Liberties of the whole Nation to the King, to be diſpoſed of by Him at his Will and Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>'Twas by vertue of this <hi>Imaginary Power,</hi> which made the King break looſe upon the Laws and govern by his Will, that He impoſed upon his Subjects ſuch Magiſtrates as he thought fitteſt for his turn, ſome true Papiſts, and others falſe Proteſtants, ſuch as would go a great way (if not through-ſtitch) to ſerve his Popiſh-Deſigns. And, tho' they were admitted without taking the Oaths in that Caſe provided, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no lawful Magiſtrates; yet all were threatned, vexed, and proſecuted, who durſt but ſay, that they had no lawful Authority.</p>
               <p>By Virtue of the ſame <hi>Power,</hi> the Kingdoms Military Defence was put into ſuch Hands as by many expreſs Laws were Inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of them. Which juſtly gave the Proteſtants ſad Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58818:10"/>of imminent Danger, ſeeing themſelves put into the Power of Men that publickly profeſſed to be in Union and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> declaring themſelves to be mortal Enemies to Proteſtants, and bound upon their Salvation to ſeek their Ruin and Deſtruction, if they perſiſted in their Religion. Thus an Army of Papiſts and Mercenaries was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and diſperſed through the Kingdom in full Peace, to the great diſquiet and terrour of the Proteſtants. Who, contrary to the Ancient Laws of the Kingdom, and the expreſs Words of the late Statutes, were conſtrained to receive thoſe Souldiers into their Houſes; whereby they were deprived of their Peace and Security at home, of a free Converſe abroad, and of the Advantages they might make otherwiſe in their Ways of living.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> was by this time grown out of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with the King, for her Stea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineſs to the Laws, and ſtrong Zeal againſt Popery. And who ſhould now grow into favour with his Majeſty, at leaſt in outward appearance, but the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Party, the Object of his Reſentment and Indignation, when he came to the Crown? The King knew how to turn the ſtream of his Kindneſs, and to ſhift from one Side to another, that loſing one Party he might make ſure of another. 'Tis true, ſome Leaders amongſt the Diſſenters made an advantage of this Turn, for their private Intereſt; but the thinking Part of them, who knew where the Snake lay, did not build much upon it. Not could the King expect much from them, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how lame and falſify'd were moſt of the Addreſſes His Majeſty receiv'd from that Party.</p>
               <p>The King, to aw the <hi>Church,</hi> erected a Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, whoſe Commiſſion was to proceed with a <hi>Non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bſtante,</hi> that is, without and againſt the Rules of our Laws. And, to pleaſe the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> He put out a Declaration for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> to all ſorts of Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; with a ſecret Intent, that none ſhould have it at laſt but the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>The Firſt was by Commiſſion, ſo far from any Colour of Law, that it was againſt moſt expreſs Laws to the Contrary; and the extent of the Commiſſion was, to take Cognizance and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58818:10"/>of all Eccleſiaſtical Matters. The Illegality and Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency whereof was ſo notoriouſly known, and the Deſign of it againſt our Religion ſo plain, that the late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (being one in the Commiſſion) refuſed to fit or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in it. For the chief Deſign of this Court was to Raiſe none to any Church Dignities but ſuch as had no Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, who cloaked their Unconcernedneſs for it with the ſpecious Pretence of Moderation; and to oppreſs ſuch of the Clergy as were of eminent Learning, Vertue, and Piety. In this Commiſſion was a Noble Peer who made publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Popiſh Religion, and who at the time of his firſt profeſſing it declared, that for a great while before he had believed that to be the only true Religion.</p>
               <p>'Twas by virtue of this Illegal Commiſſion, that the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> was Suſpended, only becauſe he refuſed to obey an Order ſent him to ſuſpend Dr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> then Rector of <hi>S. Giles,</hi> without ſo much as Citing him before him to make his own Defence, or obſerving the common Forms of Proceſs. By the ſame Court was Dr. <hi>Hough,</hi> Preſident of <hi>Magdalen Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> turned out, tho' duly choſen by the Fellows of the ſaid College; and afterwards all the Fellows of the ſaid College, only for refuſing to chuſe for their Preſident a Perſon recommended to them by the Kings Evil Counſellors Iuſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Tho' the Right of a Free Election belonged u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ſaid Fellows; and that it is expreſly provided in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> that no Man ſhall loſe L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe or Goods, but by the Law of the Land. More than that the ſaid College was wholly put into the hands of Papiſts; who by the Law of the Land, and the Statutes of the College, are altogether Inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſuch Imployments.</p>
               <p>By the King's Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty Commanded the ſame to be Read in all Churches and Chappels; whereby he would have the Clergy to be his Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to proclaim his pretended Power to Suſpend at once the Force and Uſe of our Penal Laws, made for the Security of our Religion and Property. And, when the late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and ſix other Biſhops, offered His Majeſty an humble Petition in Terms full of Reſpect, containing in ſhort the Reaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns why they could not Obey the Order ſent them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Clergy to read the Declaration in their Churches, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58818:11"/>the ſaid Biſhops were Committed to the Tower, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards brought to a Tryal, whoſe Crime was only a due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Laws. They were Acquitted, and for that piece of Juſtice Judge <hi>Holloway</hi> and Judge <hi>Powel</hi> were Diſplaced. And, becauſe their Acquittal had cauſed an univerſal Joy, ſome were brought into Trouble for their innocent Expreſſions of it.</p>
               <p>Then came out an Order from the Lords Commiſſioners, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring all the Chancellors and Arch-Deacons of <hi>England</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the Names of all ſuch as had read the King's Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience, and of thoſe that had not read it, whether they were injoyned or not injoyned to do it by their reſpective Biſhops. And 'tis obſervable, that in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi> (the Biſhop whereof was one of the Commiſſioners) near 200 Miniſters were Suſpended for not Reading the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</p>
               <p>Hitherto the Court had carried on their Intereſt bare-fac'd, at leaſt ſince the Ill-tim'd Rebellion of <hi>Monmouth</hi> and <hi>Argile;</hi> and Diſſimulation (unleſs it were to <hi>Diſſenters</hi>) had no ſhare in their Tranſactions. But, whilſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> was under Perſecution, it was thought convenient to Protect ſuch of the <hi>French</hi> Refugees as ventured to fly hither from the now raging Perſecution in <hi>France.</hi> Inſomuch that, notwithſtanding King <hi>James</hi>'s ſtrict Friendſhip and Correſpondence with the <hi>French</hi> King, His Majeſty Protected them with his Favour, and Relieved them with his Royal Briefs. But the Reaſon of the Thing is plain. The Court of <hi>France</hi> were got over the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Part, and all Things there were ripe for Action. Whereas in <hi>England</hi> the Perſecution of ſome was thought fit for a while to be Palliated by the Toleration of Others, though all equally deſign'd for Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>The ſame however of this Indulgence to the <hi>French</hi> Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants invited Multitudes of them hither, to feel the benefit of it in their diſtreſſed Condition. The Sight whereof ſtirred the Compaſſion of moſt People, even of Sober Papiſts; whilſt the Plurality of them made it their buſineſs all over the Kingdom to ſtem our Charity, by crying down the Perſecution. Which, as fam'd as it was all over <hi>Europe</hi> for the unparallell'd Cruelty of it, theſe Men had the Face to deny, repreſenting the Poor Refugees as ſo many Cut-throats and Vagabonds, whom we muſt <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58818:11"/>be forſooth aware of. A baſe Inhumane Thing it was, thus to inſult over the Oppreſſed, and to add ſo cruelly Perſecution to Perſecution. But this is true <hi>Roman</hi> Zeal.</p>
               <p>Two Things did prompt them to it. Firſt their juſt Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that this Spectacle would be a Caution for us to look to our ſelves, and ſtand upon our Gard. Secondly, That ſuch an Addition of incenſed Proteſtants to ſo great a Party as that they muſt ſtruggle with, was not at all agreeable to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. The Truth is, we ought to admire the ſingular Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God in our behalf, that this <hi>French</hi> Perſecution ſhould be ſo timed as to give us a ſeaſonable Alarm to prevent the ſame here; that our Perſecutors Precipitation and Folly ſhould be ſo great as to open their wicked Deſigns ſo early, and to ſend us over ſo many Thouſands of Witneſſes, as it were to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken us, and to let us ſee what we ought to look for, whene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Bloody Religion ſhould come to prevail among us. Whereas 'tis probable otherwiſe, that the good Nature of ſome, and the Weakneſs and Corruption of others, had put us, (to uſe Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Words) to a more melancholy and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome After-game.</p>
               <p>In the mean time Nothing was omitted to Incourage Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery upon all Accounts, tho' never ſo much againſt Law. New Popiſh Chappels and Maſs. Houſes were ſet up, New Popiſh Schools and Monaſteries Erected, four Popiſh Provincial Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops eſtabliſh'd, Prieſts and Jeſuits ſo Incouraged, that <hi>England</hi> ſwarmed with them as <hi>Egypt</hi> did of old with Frogs, Lice, and Locuſts, the Privy Council made up of Popiſh Lords, and ſome Proteſtants not much better, the Jeſuit Father <hi>Petre</hi> a Member thereof, and the chief Director of the Cabal Council, a Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio admitted, and a ſolemn Embaſſy ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Earl of <hi>Caſtlemain.</hi> All this in open Defiance to the Laws.</p>
               <p>Such was beſides the Corruption and Depravation of Juſtice in the Courts of Judicature, that the Judges muſt either be bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed by the King's Will, or expect a <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> as in the Caſe aforeſaid of <hi>Holloway</hi> and <hi>Powel.</hi> The Juries commonly returned by ſecret Contrivances and illegal Nominations, being neither (as the Law Requires) of the moſt ſufficient nor moſt indifferent of the neareſt Neighbours to the Facts in queſtion, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58818:12"/>nor by ſworn Sheriffs; So that any Mans Life or Eſtate not well affected to the then Government was in great Jeopardy, if called into Queſtion. Beſides that, by putting the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice into the hands of Papiſts, all Matters of Civil Juſtice were brought to great Uncertainties. Who being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Incapacity by Law, there lay no obligation upon any. Man to acknowledge or obey their Judgments, and all Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by them given were null and void of themſelves</p>
               <p>Thus, in few years, the Popiſh Party being become Maſters of the Affairs of the Church, of the Government of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of the Courſe of Juſtice, ſubjected them all to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotick and Arbitrary Power; that by the Aſſiſtance of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my they might be able to maintain and execute their wicked Deſigns, by eſtabliſhing Popery and Slavery.</p>
               <p>But, if our Caſe was deſperate here, it was rather worſe in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Where the whole Government was put into the hands of Papiſts, and all the Proteſtants there under a perpetual ſear of a new Maſſacre, ſuch as they fell under <hi>Anno</hi> 1641. Which made great Numbers of them leave that Kingdom, and abandon their Eſtate, in it. As for <hi>Scotland,</hi> the King declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be cloathed with <hi>Abſolute Power;</hi> and all his Subjects there bound to obey Him <hi>without reſerve;</hi> and accordingly aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med an Arbitrary Power, both over the Religion and Laws of that Kingdom. Whereby it plainly appeared what we muſt look for in <hi>England,</hi> as ſoon as Matters were duly prepared here.</p>
               <p>But, during theſe Tranſactions, the Popiſh Party grew Senſible, that the <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> being raiſed but upon a weak Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would quickly ſink; and that they could not be ſafe, unleſs the Penal Laws and the Teſts were abrogated by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Parliament, or Something like it. The King therefore made it his buſineſs to get ſuch a Parliament as would bring this to paſs.</p>
               <p>'Tis well known, that about four parts in five of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Houſe of Commons are to be choſen by Cities and Boroughs. To deſtroy therefore their Cuſtoms, Priviledges, Charters, and Governments, and to ſubſtitute therein ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates as would either ignorantly or corruptly ſerve the Kings Deſigns, Writs of <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> fell like Thunder upon <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58818:12"/>thoſe Corporations. Which were ſeconded by Inſtruments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to terrifie the Magiſtrates thereof with the King's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Diſpleaſure, if they dared to inſiſt upon their legal Right, and conteſt with the King at Law. He had Agents appointed to fright them with the vaſt Charge they muſt be at, in caſe they would be ſo bold as to ſtand it out; to poſſeſs them, that it was to no purpoſe, ſince he was reſolved to have their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at his Command; to tempt them with a Promiſe of New ones, if they would but Reſign their Old into his hands; and to threaten them, that the Names of all that refuſed it muſt be returned to the Attorney General. Beſides, that Judges were prepared to damn the Pleas of all ſuch Cities and Towns as would ſtand upon their Right. Witneſs the Cities of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and the Borough of <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tneſs,</hi> which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be Diſſolved at the King's Pleaſure; whereby their reſpective Citizens and Burgeſſ s were Disfranchiſed, and diveſted of all their ancient Cuſtoms, Freedoms, and Priviledges.</p>
               <p>This terrified moſt Cities and Boroughs into voluntary ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renders of their Charters; which brought them to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ion as to have no Magiſtrates or Officers but at the Kings Will, and during his Pleaſure. But this Proceeding of the King ſeemed the leſs ſtrange, it being but a Copy of what had been already done in the Reign of King <hi>Charles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, whereas the Election of Members of Parliament ought to be Free and Indifferent, without Pre-ingagement of the Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, by Bribes, Promiſes, or Threats, infinite were the Tricks and Artifices uſed to get ſuch a Parliament as would ſerve the King's turn. Yet none more buſie than the King himſelf, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Attempts upon the perſonal Freedom and Indifferency of all the Electors for Parliaments throughout the Kingdom. Such were his Perſonal Sollicitations in ſecret, to accept of ſuch for their Deputies in Parliament as were fit for his Deſigns, that his <hi>Cloſetting of Electors</hi> was become a By-word amongſt the People. Nor was it poſſible for Perſons that held Offices and Imyloyments of Profit and Truſt to continue in the ſame, but by their Concurrence therein with his Majeſties Pleaſure, Witneſs his ſecond Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Date of <hi>Apr.</hi> 7. 1688. wherein he declared his Mind, that none ought to be Imployed under him in the Kingdom, but ſuch as would contribute to chuſe ſuch Members of Parliament <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58818:13"/>as might do their part to finiſh what he had begun; That, in purſuance thereof, he had turned out by his Abſolute Will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Civil and Military Officers; And that he lookt upon all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers as neither good Chriſtians, nor Lovers of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries Good.</p>
               <p>To further this Deſign, the Lord Lieutenants were ordered by the King to Summon in his Name the Chief Officers and Gentlemen in their reſpective Counties, and to lay the Caſe before them, ſo as to flatter or terrify them out of the Uſe of their Freedom in Electing for Parliament. And Marks of the King's Diſpleaſure were put upon thoſe that reſolved to keep their Freedom and Indifferency to Elect worthy and fit Deputies, according to their Judgments and Conſciences.</p>
               <p>Another ſort of Men were Commiſſionated to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, Known by the Name of <hi>Regulators.</hi> Amongſt which ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Anabaptiſt Preachers were imployed, with good Weekly Allowances; who were ſent all over <hi>England,</hi> to delude People by Careſſes or Threats into a fatal Compliance with the King.</p>
               <p>By which Illeg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Practices it appears how eager the Court was to introduce the <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> Religion and Laws, by indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to free the Papiſts and Popiſh Emiſſaries from the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments of our Penal Laws againſt ſuch manifeſt A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tempts upon the Freedom. Properties, and Rights of the Realm. Which tended to nothing leſs than, Firſt, to ſubject the Laws of the Realm, and conſequently the very Rights of the Crown to the Canons of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which Rights our ancient Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Papiſts before the Reformation always indeavoured to maintain againſt the Inchroachments of the Papal See. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, To declare all the Power of Magiſtracy in Proteſtants hands to be unlawful, and all Right and Title to their Eſtates forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (by their being Proteſtants) to the Papiſts. Thirdly, To own and juſtify all Diſpenſations from <hi>Rome,</hi> with our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to all ſuch Laws of the Realm as ſhould be thought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory to the Popes Intereſt or Authority. And, Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to hold Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> and all Foreign <hi>Papiſts,</hi> tho profeſſed Enemies to the Religion and Power of the Proteſtants, ſo as to contrive with them the Suppreſſing or Extirpating of them out of the Realm.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58818:13"/>
               <p>Thus the Ax was laid to the Root, and the Train laid to blow up our Laws, Religion, and Liberties. Which was Provocation enough for a Free People, that have a ſhare in the Legiſlative Power, to ſtand up for their Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thus invaded, and to oppoſe the Exorbit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce and Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of an Executive Power, which ſhaked the very Foundation of this ancient Monarchy. Yet all was huſht, and theſe Things born with extraordinary Patience, in hopes of a Redreſs upon the next Succeſſion, whilſt the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> (now our gracious Queen) was the Heireſs apparent.</p>
               <p>But, to cut off at once theſe only remaining Hopes, who ſhould be now with Child but the Queen, after ſhe had been Childleſs ſeveral Years, and very much decayed and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Sickneſs? Which unexpected Pregnancy ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts attributed to the Kings Progreſs to St. <hi>Winifred</hi>'s Wells, others to the <hi>Bath,</hi> but moſt to the Lady of <hi>Loretto,</hi> who for the ſake of a fine Preſent made forſooth made to her by the Queens Mother (the Dutcheſs of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dena</hi>) helped her to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Son. A Son it muſt be by all means, for nothing would ſerve their turn but a Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> And, tho it proved but a Daughter, yet moſt Prieſts were of Opinion, that it would ſet aſide the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Right to the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for which they had no better Argument, than that a Daughter born after the King came to the Crown ought to ſucceed before a Daughter born before he came to it. Which argued their Ignorance.</p>
               <p>I grant, without reflecting in the leaſt upon the King, That this pretended Conception, to be real, muſt be done by a Miracle. The Queen as is before hinted, had laboured a long time under great Infirmities; and was ſo far from giving Life to another, that with much a do ſhe kept her ſelf alive. Nothing therefore but a Miracle could do that which her weak Condition made her incapable of.</p>
               <p>But, upon a ſtrict Inquiry into thoſe various Circumſtances that attend a Woman with Child, and the Want of them in the Queen, 'tis more than probable it was a meer Fiction, and a Deſign on Foot to cut off the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> from her Right to the Succeſſion. And 'tis obſervable, that, ſome <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58818:14"/>time before the Report of this unexpected and miraculous Pregnancy of the Queen, the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> had been very much preſſed in the King's Name, to declare themſelves for the Aboliſhing the Penal Laws and the Teſts. Which his Majeſty not being able to gain upon them, he was heard to ſay with much anger, that He would trouble himſelf no more with them, but they ſhould Repent it.</p>
               <p>Soon after this, the Rumor of the Queen's Conception was ſpread abroad with great Induſtry; but believed by none but Papiſts, or Perſons Popiſhly affected. For amongſt others it became a Matter of Laughter and Deriſion, and a Subjeſt for Poets Lampoons; which grew ſo common, that <hi>White-hall</hi> it ſelf was full of them</p>
               <p>But the Papiſts, who lookt upon it as a certain Way to procure their Settlement here, triumphed nevertheleſs. And the fruth is, this was the beſt VVay they could find to leſſen the growing Reputation and Power of Their Highneſſes, to weaken their Intereſt and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of the whole Body of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to incourage the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> King in the Proſecution of his cruel Deſigns againſt them, to ſtrengthen the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papiſt, and make our Corrupt and Time-ſerving Proteſtants fall in with their Party, and laſtly to poſſeſs many weak Diſſenters that their Liberty of Conſcience muſt of neceſſity be fixt in a Popiſh Succeſſion. The King therefore, to give the greater Credit to this pretended Conception, ordered a Day of Thankſgiving for it, with ſolemn Prayers to be offered unto God, for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Queen and Infant. Though he knew well enough that ſew People beſides his own Party gave any credit to it.</p>
               <p>To come now to the uſual Circumſtances that attend a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, the firſt natural Sign is the Stopping the Monthly Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. By the King's Speech in Council, it ſeems Their Majeſties had both thought fit to publiſh her Conception to have been at the Time of the Preſent made to the Ladies Image at <hi>Loretto,</hi> upon his Return to the Queen at <hi>Bath.</hi> Now 'tis very well known, that it was with Her afterward as formerly after the manner of Women; and all the Induſtry uſed to conceal it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Ineffectual, becauſe it came to the Knowledge of more than were made privy to the Plot.</p>
               <p>And, whereas in four Months time the Breaſts of a VVoman
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58818:14"/>with Child begin to ſwell and yield Milk, the Queens Breaſts never ſwelled all the time of her pretended Child-bearing, nor produced any Milk, whatever one Court Lady affirmed to the contrary. If the Queen had any Milk in her Breaſts, it was ſo much for her Intereſt and the Credit of her Cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the VVorld of her real being with Child, by giving that ſignal Demonſtration of it, that I had rather think her Majeſty wanted Milk, than ſo much common Prudence as to make it appear, in caſe ſhe had any. And we are very well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that none of the Ladies proper to be VVitneſſes could ever obtain the ſatisfaction to ſee a drop of Milk from her Breaſts.</p>
               <p>The ſame Reaſon we have to disbelieve the Quickening of the Child in her VVomb, however induſtriouſly it was ſpread abroad. For the feeling of its Motion was never vouchſafed to any competent VVitneſſes of it which would have been a main Proof of her Pregnancy, had there been any ſuch Thing. And therefore 'twas expected, to give the ſuſpicious Kingdom a Ground to believe the Queen to be really with Child, that her Majeſty would have made ſome of the Proteſtant Ladies of her Bed-Chamber ſenſible of ſo great a Proof of her being in the Codition ſhe pretended.</p>
               <p>Another manifeſt Sign of the true natural Progreſs of a Great Belly, is the Diſtenſion of all the Parts of the Body that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the Womb. The Queen indeed had her Belly exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly copped up, and high. But, as it was obſerved by skilful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, all the outward Parts of her Body that incircle the Womb were of the ſame proportion that they were at other times. And, when they minded her Majeſty walking, and lookt upon her behind and on each ſide, they could ſee no appearance in her of a Great Bellied Woman. Her Bodies were made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out alteration. And, during all the laſt four Months, when ſhe was to change her Linnen, She always withdrew from her Chamber with two or three Italian Women, and retired into her Cloſet, or ſome other private Room, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to her former uſual Courſe; and would not ſuffer any of the Proteſtant Ladies of the Bed-Chamber to ſee her ſhift her ſelf, as they had conſtantly done.</p>
               <p>All theſe are ſtrong Preſumptions, that the Queen's Great Belly was but a falſe Appearance to delude the Nation. But
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58818:15"/>there are other Circumſtances, that create as great a Prejudice againſt it.</p>
               <p>In the Preparation for Her Majeſties ſuppoſed Delivery it was expected, that early Notice ſhould be given to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the Blood of her expected Travel, and of the Place of her Reſidence at ſuch time; that proper Noble Matrons, and others, might prepare themſelves, and attend there in their behalf, who, by their Teſtimonies might have for ever ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and ſilenced all Suſpicions of Fraud or Impoſture. It was hoped at leaſt, that the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> would have been preſent, to ſee what was brought forth. But Care was taken to adviſe her, when ſhe wanted aſtringent Medicines, to go to the looſening Waters of the Bath; and to keep her 80 miles diſtant, till the ſuppoſed Prince ſhould be born.</p>
               <p>To conceal the Time and intended Place for this fictitious Travel, ſuch Artifices were uſed, that no body could tell when nor where this Play was to be acted. Sometimes the Queen was to lye at <hi>Richmond,</hi> ſometimes at <hi>Windſor,</hi> another time at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> tho St. <hi>James</hi>'s was the Place appointed. And, when her Majeſty declared ſhe would lye at St. <hi>James</hi>'s on the <hi>Saturday</hi> at night, which was the Night before her preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed Travel and Delivery, the Warning was ſo very ſhort, that with much ado her Lodgings could be got ready time enough.</p>
               <p>That very night the Queen was late at Cards, without any Sign of fore-running Pains of a Woman whoſe Travel approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, nor is any pretended to have been in the Night<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And it does not ſo much as appear, that the uſual Inſtruments of Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives, whereupon they commonly place all Women of Quali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty in their Time of Travel, were got in readineſs. So that every Thing was carried on and managed by her Majeſty, as if ſhe choſe rather to confirm the general Opinion of the People, that this was but a pious Cheat, than to be at the trouble of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the parts of a VVoman with Child.</p>
               <p>The Time of the Day fixt upon for this Travel, and the Room it ſelf wherein it was to be acted, are two other unlucky Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that mainly fortify the National Prejudice againſt this pretended Prince. The Travel was contrived to be at Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time on the <hi>Sunday,</hi> between the hours of nine and ten in the morning, that the Buſineſs might be over before the Proteſtant Ladies were come from Church, and that the Aſſiſtant <hi>Matrons</hi> might be free to act their Parts as they did.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58818:15"/>
               <p>In the Room there was a private Door within the Ruel of the Bed, leading into an Inner Room, from whence a Child might be ſecretly brought, and put unſeen into the Bed. And by that Privy Door all the Tranſactions were managed. 'Tis true, ſome Lords and Ladies were brought into the Bed-Chamber, but only to be ſeen in the Room, and that their Names might be publiſhed as VVitneſſes of the Queen's being Delivered, tho they ſaw nothing that was done.</p>
               <p>For the Queen lay in Bed with all the Curtains round cloſe drawn, whilſt the Midwife and her Confederates ſeemed very buſy about Her Majeſty in the dark, none ſeeing what they did. Nor do's it appear, that Her Majeſty had any of thoſe natural Signs which uſually attend a Travel, and ſuch as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hidden. Her Labour was ſhort and eaſy, far beyond what could be expected from her State of Body, debilitated with long lingering Infirmities. VVhich might be ſo contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, leſt the Child that was got in the Bed ſhould be ſtifled by the Cloſeneſs of it.</p>
               <p>The Jobb being thus finely over, ſomething cloſe covered was by the Midwife delivered to one of the Confederate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and both haſtned with it through the Privy Door into the next Room, without declaring what it was, a Prince or a Princeſs. VVhich looks ſomething odd of the Midwife, to quit her Attending and Aſſulting the Queen, when her At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance and Skill were both ſo neceſſary to preſerve her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Life, if ſhe had really brought forth either a Son or a Daughter.</p>
               <p>Nor was the Child heard to Cry, which is the common and moſt conſtant natural Sign of the Birth of a living Child. Which might be, becauſe the Child that was brought in was prepared to ſleep, to prevent its Crying before it was conveyed into the Bed, and ſlept on till it was gradually awaked.</p>
               <p>The King, after ſome time, leaving the Lords of the Council in the Bed-Chamber (who had waited all this while to no more purpoſe, than if they had been ten miles off) with-drew into the inner Room, where the ſuppoſed Prince was. And ſoon after the News was brought them, that a Prince was born. VVhereupon ſome went away, and others ſtaid yet a while, to have a ſight of this New-born Prince. VVho being ſhewn unto them, the King ſaid, That he had now a Son, a ſtrong, <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58818:16"/>and lively Prince. VVhich gave occaſion for a Joke, even amongſt the meaneſt ſort of Child-bearing Women, <hi>That ſuch a Child of about Eight Months was as great a Miracle as the Queens Conception.</hi> For, by their Majeſties Reckoning, this ſuppoſed Prince was but the Product of eight Months and four Days; and to ſee ſuch an untimely Birth ſo ſtrong and lively, eſpecially from ſo weak a Mother, is rare, and almoſt paſt Belief.</p>
               <p>Nor was the Matter much mended by ſaying, That it was frequent amongſt Child-bearing VVomen to Miſre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kon; or by perſuading the Queen to declare, contrary to her firſt Reckoning (which ſhe kept to ſeveral Weeks after her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Delivery) That ſhe had miſcounted the Time of her Conception, and that ſhe knew her ſelf to be with Child be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Uſe of the <hi>Bath.</hi> Strange! that Her Majeſty ſhould be then with Child, and yet have her Monthly Courſes, as ſhe had in her Journey to the <hi>Bath,</hi> and four Days after the Kings going from thence. That, knowing her ſelf with Child at that time, ſhe ſhould not acquaint her Phyſicians with it; the meaneſt of whom might have told Her Majeſty, That her Bathing would probably deſtroy the Embryo. And that Her Majeſty ſhould not conſider, this would ſpoil the Story of the Miracle of <hi>Loretto,</hi> ſaid to be performed at the King's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Bath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are Things ſo Inconſiſtent, and altogether ſo Irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable, that they would be hiſſed at in any Judicious and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Court of Judicature. But any Thing will go down with a ſort of Men that can digeſt Contradictions, and whoſe Zeal to their Religion can make them believe at random what they ſee not, and not to believe what they ſee.</p>
               <p>If the Queen's pretended Conception was Miraculous, the Progreſs of her Great Belly, and her Delivery, were as Preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural. Nay, the very Conſequents of her Delivery were no leſs wonderful, ſo that it was all but one continued Miracle. To ſee a Queen, at the beſt but tender and weak, yet free from any Danger of her Life after an Untimely Birth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Feaver, or ſo much as the uſual Redundancy of Milk, theſe are ſuch Bleſſings from Heaven as may paſs for Miracles. But, as the Miracle of the Conception was ſpoiled by ſhifting the Reckoning, ſo it is to be feared that the reſt was all of a piece.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58818:16"/>
               <p>From what is ſaid, upon very ſure Evidence, I leave the World to judge what Ground there is to believe the ſuppoſed Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> to be born of the Queen. I confeſs it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hard to think, That a Father ſhould be ſo Unjuſt and Unnatural, as to put by his own Lawful Children from their Succeſſion to the Crown, to make Room for an Interloper, a ſuppoſititious Child. Beſides the Affront put, 1. Upon the two Princes, joined in Wedlock to his Daughters, and having thereby a Matrimonial Right to the Crown. 2. Upon three Kingdoms, by Impoſing a ſtrange (tho innocent) Child upon them to be the next Succeſſor, and conſequently to receive in time Homage and Allegiance of all the Subjects thereof, the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty, with all dutiful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his Commands. 3. Upon all Foreign States, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Powers, and Principalities, by ſetting up a Sham-Prince, who being upon the Throne muſt be lookt upon and reſpected as a great King and a lawful Prince, in all their Treaties and Negotiations with him.</p>
               <p>But what is not a blind Zeal capable of? To Settle a Popiſh Succeſſor in theſe Kingdoms was ſuch a piece of meritorious Service to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that nothing could indear the King more to her, than the doing of it. What Iſſue he had then alive were too much dipt in Hereſy; and nothing could bring them off from it, no not ſo much as to conſent to the Repealing of thoſe two Bug-bears, the Penal Laws and the Teſts.</p>
               <p>But, ſuppoſe this Prince were really born of the Queen, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which there are ſo many ſtrong Preſumptions, 'tis a Thing unaccountable why the Queen ſhould be ſo ſhy all the time of her Child-bearing to give that publick Satisfaction about it which was reaſonably expected from her Majeſty. The Nation was poſſeſſed, it was all but a Trick. It had been there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore but common Prudence in the Queen to Undeceive us as far as it lay in her power, even for the Child's ſake in her Womb. If her Majeſty had Milk in her Breaſts, what dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution to her Glory had it been to let her Proteſtant Ladies ſee but ſome Drops of it? If, when the Child ſtirred in the Womb, but two or three true-hearted Proteſtant Ladies had been admitted to feel thoſe Motions, it had gone a great way to ſilence all Gainſayers, and to quicken the very Nation into another Belief. When Her Majeſty was near the time of her <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58818:17"/>Travel, to what purpoſe was the Place appointed for her Lying In ſo concealed, that no Proteſtant could tell where to find Her? And why muſt a Room at laſt be choſen at S. <hi>James</hi>'s, with a private Door within the Ruel of the Bed, leading into another Room, which alone was enough to create a Suſpicion? To which add a total Neglect, and abſolute ſlighting of all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Rules of Law and Juſtice about needful Witneſſes of the Birth of a Prince and Heir to the Crown. So that, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this pretended Prince to be really born of the Queen, it muſt be granted, that Things were ſo managed from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end, as if the Court intended to make the Thing ſtill more doubtful, and the Suſpicion the ſtronger. And, if that was their Aim, they have hit the Nail on the Head.</p>
               <p>Thus, the Birth of this ſuppoſed Prince not being lawfully Witneſſed, Her Royal Highneſs the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> had no Reaſon to depart from her Claim of Heireſs apparent to the Crown, or to Reſign it to him; But rather to complain to the World of the Wrong done her, by ſuffering a ſuppoſed Child to ſteal upon her Right, and aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me the Name of Prince and Heir apparent to the Crown.</p>
               <p>Nor was it her part to prove him a Counterfeit, it being a Rule by the Laws and Cuſtoms of all Civil Governments for any one that claims to be the lawful Son of a family, to being in legal Proofs for it. Her Royal Highneſs had been hitherto acknowledged to be the Heireſs apparent of the Crown; and nothing could legally debar her from that Claun but a true born Prince, with ſuch Legal Witneſſes as would ſatisfie the Nation that it was ſo. The Want of which in this Caſe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> in her full, Claim to the next Succeſſion.</p>
               <p>To vindicate which Claim, and to Secure withal the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Intereſt in theſe Kingdoms, His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> upon the earneſt and humble Application of ſeveral of the Lords both Spiritual and Temporal, came over from <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with a competent Force. Which leads me to my Third Part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58818:17"/>
               <head>THE HISTORY Of the LATE REVOLUTION</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>PART III.</hi> Shewing Our Wonderful Deliverance by our preſent King <hi>William,</hi> and our Great Happineſs therein.</head>
               <p>THings were now brought to an Extremity, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a miraculous Providence could Reſcue us from our Enemies. To which end it pleaſed God to raiſe His Highneſs, the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> A Magnanimous, Wiſe, and Religious Prince; whoſe Illuſtrious Family ſeems to have been appointed by Providence, ever ſince the Reformation, for the Preſervation of God's Church, and a Check to Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
               <p>This Prince being penetrated with the diſmal Account he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, Zea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of the <hi>French</hi> Perſecution, and poſſeſſed with a and King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt the Known Combination of King <hi>James</hi> the Reformation, for the Inſlaving all <hi>Europe,</hi> and Rooting out to oppoſe their Amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d, with God's help in ſo juſt a Cauſe, that had been hitherto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Idolatrous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deſigns. <hi>England,</hi> King's Greatneſs, was the moſt likely, Inſtrument of the <hi>French</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reduced to its
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58818:18"/>proper and natural Courſe, to influence and procure his Fall. The Provocations were great on King <hi>James</hi>'s ſide, by his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Methods of Government contrary to Law and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Liberty, by his Attempts upon their Religion, and by Impoſing upon them a Succeſſor juſtly ſuſpected of being a Stranger to the Royal Blood.</p>
               <p>For the Redreſſing which Abuſes, by a Free and Full Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, His Royal Highneſs undertook the late famous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition; which God was pleaſed to Crown with Glory and Succeſs, to the Amazement of all <hi>Europe,</hi> the Joy of all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Men, and the Terrour of Tyranny. In order to which ſuitable Preparations had been made in <hi>Holland,</hi> both by Sea and Land, to defend his Highneſs from the Violence of all ſuch as ſhould oppoſe Him. Which were carried on with that wonderful Secrecy, tho' the Secret was diſperſed amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that the Sagacious Count <hi>D' Avaux,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador at the <hi>Hague,</hi> could not ſift out the Meaning of it, till all Things were in great forwardneſs, and the Prince almoſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take Shipping. Whoſe Forces conſiſted of about 13000 Men, Horſe, Foot, and Dragoons; and (which is remarkable) a good part of them Papiſts. For the Tranſporting whereof, with all Things neceſſary, there were 300 Fly-boats, Pinks, and other Veſſels, under the Convoy of 50 Capital Men of War, 26 Smaller, and 25 Fire-ſhips.</p>
               <p>But, before his Setting out, He publiſhed a Declaration, to ſatisfy the World with the Juſtice of his Undertaking. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, having fairly ſhewn the manifeſt and undeniable Invaſion of the Laws and Liberties of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Kings.<note place="margin">The Sum of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Evil Counſellors, He Declares, <hi>That, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the moſt earneſt Sollicitations of a great many Lords both Spiritual and Temporal, and of many Gentlemen and other Subjects of all Ranks, for the Relief of theſe Three Kingdoms, He thought ſit to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> over into</hi> England, <hi>with a Force ſufficient (by the Bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> intended to defend him from Violence. That his Exped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>wful Parliament for no other End, but to have a Free Secure to the whole Na-Aſſembled, as ſoon as poſſible, in Laws, Rights, and Liberties, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tion the free Injoyment of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>vernment, to preſerve the Proteſtant under a Juſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch as would live peaceably under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58818:18"/>(as becomes good Subjects) from all Perſecution upon the account of their Religion, even</hi> Papiſts <hi>themſelves not excepted; ſo that there might be no more Danger of the Nations falling at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time hereafter under Arbitrary Government.</hi> He further De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>That to this Parliament he would Refer the Inquiry into the Birth of the pretended Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>and of all Things relating to it, or to the Right of Succeſſion.</hi> And, for the Executing of this his juſt Deſign, <hi>He Invites and Requires all Perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, all the Peers of the Realm both Spiritual and Temporal, all Lords Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieutenants, and all Gentlemen, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, and other Commons of all Ranks, to Come and Aſſiſt Him againſt all ſuch as ſhould indeavour to Oppoſe Him. Whereby all thoſe Miſeries might be prevented, which muſt needs follow upon the Nations being kept under Arbitrary Government and Slavery; and all the Violences and Diſorders which had Overturned the whole Conſtitution of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Government, might be fully Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed in a Free and Legal Parliament.</hi> Then He concludes to this purpoſe. <hi>That he would take Care, as ſoon as the Nations were brought to a State of Quiet, that a Parliament ſhould be called in</hi> Scotland, <hi>for Reſtoring the ancient Conſtitution of that Kingdom, and for bringing the Matters of Religion to ſuch a Settlement, that the People might live eaſy and happy, and for putting an end to all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Violences that had been committed there in a courſe of ſo many Years. And, as for</hi> Ireland, <hi>That he would ſtudy to bring that Kingdom to ſuch a State, that the Settlement there might be religiouſly obſerved, and that the Proteſtant and Britiſh Intereſt there might be ſecured.</hi> Finally, <hi>That He would Indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, by all poſſible Means, to procure ſuch an Eſtabliſhment i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all the Three Kingdoms, that they might all live in a happy Union and Correſpondency together; and that the Proteſtant Religion, the Peace, Honour, and Happineſs of theſe Nations might be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed upon laſting Foundations.</hi> This Declaration being Given under His Highneſſes Hand and Seal at his Court in the <hi>Hague, Oct.</hi> 10. (New-ſtyle) 1688. was accordingly thus ſigned, <hi>William Henry Prince of Orange,</hi> and by by His Highneſſes Command, <hi>C. Huygens.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58818:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The King, having had Notice of the Prince's Deſign but a Month before his Highneſs ſet out from <hi>Holland,</hi> hurried away from <hi>Windſor</hi> (where the Court then was) to <hi>White-hall,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Chatham,</hi> to get as much of his Fleet in readineſs as could be done in ſo ſhort a Warning. He came to <hi>White-hall</hi> Sept. 18. and the next Day he went down the River to <hi>Chatham;</hi> the Queen and the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> with the whole Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, returning in a great hurry the Day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty had, ſometime before, ſignified his Pleaſure to Call a Parliament to meet in <hi>November</hi> next, and Writs of Summons were iſſued out accordingly. Upon this Intelligence He did put out a plauſible Declaration, dated <hi>Sept.</hi> 21ſt. wherein He declared <hi>His Royal Purpoſe to Indeavour at the next Seſſions a Legal Eſtabliſhment of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Liberty of Conſcience for all his Subjects, together with his Reſolution In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably to Preſerve the Church of</hi> England <hi>as by Law Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, excepting the Penal Clauſes. And, to remove all Fears and Apprehenſions that the Legiſtative Power would be Ingroſſed by the</hi> Roman Catholicks, <hi>and turned againſt Proteſtants, He declared his Willingneſs that they ſhould remain Incapable to be Members of the Houſe of Commons. As for the Election of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament, His Majeſty by this His Declaration gave ſtrict Orders, that all Things relating thereto ſhould be done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Immediately after the publiſhing of the ſaid Declaration, the King was pleaſed <hi>to Authorize and Impower the Lords Lieutenants of the ſeveral Counties to Grant Deputations to ſuch Gentlemen as had been lately Removed from being Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Lieutenants.</hi> And His Majeſty gave alſo Directions to the Lord Chancellor <hi>to put into the Commiſſion of the Peace ſuch Gentlement as had been laid aſide, and ſhould be recommended by the ſaid Lords Lieutenants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, upon the Attendance of ſeveral of the Biſhops on the King, His Majeſty was pleaſed, amongſt other Gracious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, to let them know, <hi>That he would ſignify his Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for taking off the Suſpenſion of the Lord Biſhop of</hi> London. Which was done accordingly.</p>
               <p>Then came out his Proclamation, under the Date of <hi>Sept.</hi>
28th. Wherein He firſt informs his People of <hi>a great and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58818:19"/>Invaſion from</hi> Holland, <hi>to be ſpeedily made in a Hoſtile Manner upon this his Kingdom;</hi> And then ſolemnly Conjures all his Subjects <hi>heartily to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite together in the Defence of Him, and their Native Country, as the only Way (under God) to defeat and fruſtrate the Principal Hope and Deſign of his and their Enemies.</hi> But, <hi>whereas he did intend to have met his Parliament in</hi> November <hi>next, He found it neceſſary, in regard of this ſtrange and unreaſonable Attempt from our Neighbouring Country, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of Provocation, to recall the Writs iſſued forth, with Orders to ſurceaſe all further Proceedings thereon.</hi> Then He proceeds to give the neceſſary Charge to all Lords Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants and Deputy Lieutenants, <hi>to uſe their beſt and utmoſt Indeavours, to Reſiſt, Rebel, and Suppreſs his Enemies, who came with ſuch Confidence and great Preparations to Invade and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer theſe his Kingdoms.</hi> And laſtly, <hi>does moſt expreſly and ſtrictly Injoin and Prohibit all his Subjects from giving any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Aid, Aſſiſtance, Countenance, or Succour, or from hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Correſpondence with theſe his Enemies, or any of their Complices, upon Pain of High Treaſon, and being proceeded againſt with the utmoſt Severity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Within four Days after came out His Majeſties moſt <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and General Pardon;</hi> but with ſuch Intricate Clauſes as reſolved the Pardon into little or nothing.</p>
               <p>The King upon this, having received ſeveral Complaints of great Abuſes and Irregularities committed in the late Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of the Corporations, <hi>Authorized and Required the Lords Lieutenants of the ſeveral Counties to Inform themſelves of all ſuch Abuſes and Irregularities within their Lieutenancies, and to make forthwith Report thereof to His Majeſty, together with what they conceived fit to be done for Redreſſing the ſame. Whereupon His Majeſty would give ſuch farther Orders as ſhould be requiſite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Thing was His Majeſties Appointing the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> as Viſior of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, to Settle that Society Regularly and Statutably.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then a Proclamation, <hi>for Reſtoring Corporations to their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Charters, Liberties, Rights and Franchiſes.</hi> Followed by an Order from the King and Council, under His Majeſties Signet and Sign-Manual, to <hi>Remove, Diſplace, and Diſcharge all manner of Officers and Magiſtrates of Cities, Boroughs, and <pb n="36" facs="tcp:58818:20"/>Towns Corporate, which had or claimed ſuch Offices or Places by Charter, Patent, or Grant from the late King, or from Him, ſince the Year</hi> 1679. <hi>Except ſuch Cities and Towns whoſe Deeds of Surrender were Inrolled, or againſt whom Judgments in</hi> Quo War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranto <hi>were entred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Oct.</hi> 2d. the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Sheriffs, with ſeveral other Eminent Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> attending the King, His Majeſty was pleaſed to tell them, <hi>That out of his Concern for the Peace and VVelfare of the City, and as a Mark of the great Confidence. He had in them at this time that the Kingdom was threatned with an Invaſion, He had reſolved to reſtore to them their Ancient Charter and Priviledges, and to put them into the ſame Condition they were at the time of the Judgment pronounced againſt them upon the,</hi> Quo Warranto, <hi>that ſo they might be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enabled to ſerve him with that Duty and Loyalty which they had given the King his Brother and Himſelf ſo many Teſtimonies of, and upon which His Majeſty did depend. VVhereupon the King was pleaſed to give expreſs Commands to the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of</hi> England, <hi>and the Attorney General, to prepare ſuch Grant or Inſtrument of Reſtauration and Confirmation as ſhould be requiſite, and that the ſame ſhould be forthwith Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having been Exerciſed to the Right and to the Left, Backward and Forward, We found our ſelves at laſt much <hi>As we were</hi> at firſt. And, had there been any rational Hopes of Continuing thus, without any further Breach, theſe gentle Methods (tho upon a forced Put) would have gone perhaps a great way to turn the Stream, and to quiet the People. But, what Aſſurance could be had of having theſe our Rights continued to us any longer than what would ſerve our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Turn?</p>
               <p>The Prince therefore, hearing of theſe Retractations, which proceeded more from Fear than any Principle of Juſtice, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed an Additional Declaration, Given under his Hand and Seal at his Court at the <hi>Hague</hi> the 24th. (being our 14th.) of <hi>October,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Addition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> in theſe following Words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After VVe had prepared and printed Our Declaration, VVe have underſtood, That the Subverters of the Religion and Laws of thoſe Kingdoms, hearing of Our Preparations to aſſist the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58818:20"/>againſt them, have begun to Retract ſome of the Arbitrary and Deſpotick Powers that they had aſſumed, and to Vacate ſome of their unjuſt Judgments and Decrees. The Senſe of their Guilt, and the Diſtruſt of their Force, have induced them to Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to the City of</hi> London <hi>ſome ſeeming Relief from their great Oppreſſions, hoping thereby to quiet the People, and to divert them from demanding a ſecure Re-eſtabliſhment of their Religion and Laws, under the ſhelter of our Arms. They do alſo give out, that we intend to Conquer and I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſlave the Nation. Therefore We have thought fit to add a few VVords to our Declaration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are confident, that no Perſons can have ſuch hard Thoughts of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, as to imagine, that We have any other Deſign in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, than to procure a Settlement of the Religion and of the Liberties and Properties of the Subjects upon ſo ſure a Foundation, that there may be no danger of the Nation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Relapſing into the like Miſeries at any time hereafter. And, as the Forces We have brought along with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s are utterly diſpropertioned to that wicked Deſign of Conquering the Nation, if We were capable of intending it; So the great Numbers of the Principal Nobility and Gentry, that are Men of Eminent Quality and Eſtates, and Perſons of known Integrity and Zeal both for the Religion and Government of</hi> England, <hi>many of them being alſo diſtinguiſhed by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Fidelity to the Crown, who do both accompany <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s in this Expedition, and have earneſtly ſollicited <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to it, will cover us from all ſuch malicious Inſinuations. For it is not to be imagined that either thoſe who have Invited <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, or thoſe that are already come to aſſiſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, can joyn in a wicked Attempt of Conqueſt, to make void their own lawful Titles to their Honours, Eſtates, and Intereſts. We are alſo confident, that all Men ſee how little weight there is to be laid on all Promiſes and Ingagements that can be now made, ſince there has been ſo little Regard had in time paſt to the moſt ſolemn Promiſes. And, as that imperfect Redreſs that is now offered is a plain Confeſſion of thoſe Violations of the Government that We have ſet forth, ſo the Defectiveneſs of it is no leſs appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. For they lay down nothing which they may not take up at pleaſure, reſerving intire, and not ſo much as mentioned their Claims, and Pretences to an <hi>Arbitrary and Deſpotick Power;</hi> which has been the Root of all their Oppreſſion, and of the Total Subverſion of the Government. And it is plain, that there can be no Redreſs nor Remedy offered but in Parliament, by a Declaration of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58818:21"/>Rights of the Subjects that have been invaded, and not by any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Acts of Grace, to which the extremity of their Affairs has driven them. Therefore it is that we have thought fit to Declare, that we will refer all to a Free Aſſembly of the Nation in a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>James,</hi> having notice of theſe Declarations, which touched him to the quick, and made him very uneaſy, His Majeſty forthwith put out a Proclamation, dated Nov. 2d. to forewarn all his Subjects <hi>not to publiſh, diſperſe, repeat, or hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſaid Treaſonable Papers and Declarations, or any of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> any other Paper or Papers, of ſuch like nature; Nor preſume to Read, Receive, Conceal, or keep them, or any of them, without Diſcovering or Revealing the ſame with all ſpeed to ſome of the Privy Council, or to ſome of the Judges, Juſtices of the Peace, or other publick Magiſtrates, upon Peril of being Proſecuted according to the utmoſt Severity of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Fortnight before this a Proclamation was come out, ſtrictly charging all the Lords Lieutenants and Deputy Lieutenants of the Counties adjoyning to the Sea, and all other Officers Civil and Military within the ſaid Counties, <hi>to cauſe the Coaſts to be carefully watched, and upon the firſt approach of the Enemy to cauſe all manner of Cattel ſit for Burden and Draught, and not actually imployed in His or the Countrey's Service, to be Driven and Removed by the ſpace at leaſt of twenty Miles from the Place where the Enemy ſhould attempt to Land, and to ſecure the ſame in ſuch effectual Manner, that they might not fall into the Hands or Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of any of His Enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Proclamation was ſet forth, under the Date of <hi>Octob.</hi> 26. <hi>to Reſtrain the Spreading of falſe News, in this time of publick Danger, by Charging all Officers and Magiſtrates whatſoever to take effectual Care for the ſpeedy Apprehenſion, Proſecution, and ſevere Puniſhment of all Offenders herein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, there came out a Declaration, dated <hi>Nov.</hi> 6. wherein His Majeſty, after ſome grievous Reflections on this pretended <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural Attempt of the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>to Invade his Kingdoms, and the many Miſchiefs and Calamities which an Army of Foreigners and Robels muſt unavoidably bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on His People,</hi> Charges His Highneſs with <hi>Aſſuming the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Style in his Declaration, by Requiring therein the Peers of the Realm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to Obey, and Aſſiſt him in the Execution of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,</hi> 
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58818:21"/>whereas the words are, <hi>to Come and Aſſiſt him,</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the Caſe very much, and makes the Exception void. Then He exclaims upon the Prince's <hi>Calling in queſtion the Legitimacy of the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>his Son and Heir apparent, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there were at his Birth ſo many Witneſſes of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nqueſtionable Credit.</hi> And, whereas the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had Declared, that he would ſubmit all to the Determination of a Free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, His Majeſty by this his Declaration indeavours to poſſeſs his People, that <hi>a Parliament could not be free, ſo long as there was an Army of Forreigners in the Heart of his Kingdom,</hi> and declared his Reſolution <hi>to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l one as ſoon as his Kingdoms ſhould be delivered from this Invaſion, with Aſſurances of Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and Redreſſing all the Juſt Complaints and Grievances of His good Subjects, and of Maintaining them in their Religion, Liberties, and Properties. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which Conſiderations, and the Obligations of their Duty, and natural Allegiance, He promiſes Himſelf, that they will readily and heartily Concur and Joyn with him in the intire Suppreſſion and Repelling of thoſe his Enemies and Rebellious Subjects, coming to Diſturb the Peace of theſe his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King had hitherto turned every Stone, to bring off his People from Joyning with the Prince, with daily Retractations, Promiſes and Threats, Proclamations, and Declarations. Nay ſome few Addreſſes were procured, full of horror and amazement at this intended <hi>Invaſion,</hi> as they called it, and of the Subſcribers Impatience to ſhew their Zeal for the King's Service, by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing their Lives and Fortunes for the ſupport of his Crown and Dignity. Such was the humble Addreſs of the Juſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> ſubſcribed unto by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Gentlemen of the ſaid County. Another from the Mayor, Aldermen, and Common-Council of <hi>Exeter.</hi> A third from the Mayor, Aldermen, Bailifs, and Citizens of the City of <hi>Carliſle.</hi> And, by Sir <hi>Thomas Haggerſtons</hi> Report, then Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Berwick,</hi> the People of that Place were ſo tranſported with Loyalty to the King, and poſſeſſed with ſuch a Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and abhorrence of this <hi>Invaſion,</hi> that they not only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to venture their Lives and Fortunes in the Defence of the King's Perſon and Government; but deſired withal, that His Majeſty would be graciouſly pleaſed to ſend down Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions for the Raiſing a Regiment of Inhabitants, to be aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58818:22"/>to the King's ſtanding Forces there, as Occaſion ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</p>
               <p>All this the <hi>Gazets</hi> took great care to acquaint us with; as alſo to let us know thoſe Noble Peers and others who, upon the News of this miſcalled <hi>Invaſion,</hi> humbly offered their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to His Majeſty. Amongſt which was his Grace the late Duke of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> to whom the King gave a Commiſſion to raiſe a Regiment of Foot.</p>
               <p>The King had a gallant Army, but moſt of them were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and not a few true Engliſh Men, readier to draw the Sword for the Defence of the Proteſtant Religion and the Liberty of <hi>England,</hi> than for the Maintenance of thoſe two Inſeparable Monſters, <hi>Popery and Slavery.</hi> The People ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally waited for the Princes Coming with great Impatience, and could not conceal the Joy which the Expectation of him had diffus'd over and the Kingdom. So that, if this were an Invaſion, one could every where read Treaſon in their Faces, and a Man could ſcarce turn about but he met with a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
               <p>They that knew not the North from the South, or the Eaſt from the Weſt, fell learning of the Compaſs, to find out how the Wind fat, whilſt they longed for that Wind which muſt bring over the Prince. So mindful were the People of the late Attempts upon their Religion, Laws, and Liberties, that they look't upon Him as their <hi>Saviour,</hi> whom the Court Party called <hi>Invader.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such was the ſtate of Things here, when the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> having long waited for a favourable Wind, did at laſt ſet out from <hi>Holland</hi> with His great Fleet, which lay in the <hi>Flats</hi> near the <hi>Brill.</hi> This was <hi>October</hi> 19. (old Style) 1688, when his Highneſs, attended by Mareſchal <hi>de Schomberg</hi> as General, with many other great Officers, and Perſons of Quality of ſeveral Nations, ſet Sail about four a Clock in the Afternoon. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be more glorious than his Setting out, but nothing more diſmal than what followed ſoon after. So furious a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt did ariſe in the Night as wholly diſperſed that prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fleet, and gave great Apprehenſions of its Loſs. VVhen <hi>Holland,</hi> that had ſeen but the day before the whole Fleet ſail together in the greateſt Splendour, ſaw now but ſeattered Ships
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58818:22"/>return into its Harbour, not without ſome Damage. Which proved for ſome time a great Mortification to the Proteſtant Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whilſt the Roman Catholicks lookt upon it as an Indication of God's Anger, an ill Omen to the Prince, and a terrible War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to His Highneſs not to Attempt any Thing againſt the Church Intereſt. In ſhort, they preſently concluded his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs muſt let fall his Deſign. And 'tis obſervable, that, upon the News of it here, there was a Demurr put upon the Buſineſs of <hi>Magdalen Colledge;</hi> which ſhewed ſtill what they would be at, if the Prince had any way failed in his Deſign.</p>
               <p>But the whole Fleet came at laſt to ſeveral Ports of <hi>Holland,</hi> without ſo much as one Ship caſt away. Only one Man, and
4 or 500 Horſes were loſt, which were thrown Over-board. So that his Highneſs, admiring God's Providential Goodneſs in ſo great a Trial, reſolved to purſue his Heroick Deſign with the firſt Opportunity. And, whatever Application might be made unto him to diſſuade him from any further Attempt, he declared, That his Word was too far ingaged, and his Honour lay too much at Stake, for any Danger to deter him from the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the firſt, or from Saving the laſt as far as it lay in his power. That, as He was ſatisfied with the Juſtice of his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, ſo He was fully convinced of God's merciful Goodneſs in Saving the whole Fleet from ſo apparent a Danger, which he took as a good Omen. Accordingly He ordered all Things to be got in rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineſs, and a ſpeedy Recruit of Horſes to be made.</p>
               <p>About <hi>Octob.</hi> 30. the Wind turning Eaſterly, and blowing freſh, Orders were given to Set out with all Speed. And two Days after, <hi>Nov.</hi> 1. about Three in the Afternoon, the whole Fleet, now increaſed to a greater Number did ſet Sail. Which, being commanded by Admiral <hi>Herbert,</hi> was divided into three Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, the <hi>Red, White,</hi> and <hi>Blue,</hi> according to the Colour of their reſpective Flags. The Prince was in the <hi>Brill,</hi> a new Ship of about 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Guns; Whoſe Flag was Engliſh Colours, with this Motto impaled thereon, <hi>The Proteſtant Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of England;</hi> and underneath, <hi>I Will Maintain It.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>Red</hi> Squadron belonged the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Forces, conſiſting of ſix Foot Regiments, commanded by Major General <hi>Mackay.</hi> To the <hi>VVhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> the Prince's <hi>Gards</hi> and the <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburghers,</hi> under the Command of Count <hi>Solms.</hi> And the <hi>Blue</hi> 
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58818:23"/>Squadron contained the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Forces, commanded by Count <hi>Naſſaw.</hi> Every Ship had a diſtinctive Mark, whereby it was Known unto what Squadron ſhe belonged. And, when Night came upon them, all the Ships ſet out their Lights, which made a moſt glorious Shew upon the Sea; the Princes Ship ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving three Lanthorns, the other Men of War two each, and each other Ship one. All which at a diſtance appeared like ſo many Stars, moving upon the Water.</p>
               <p>The Wind and VVeather continuing Fair, on <hi>Saturday Nov.</hi>
3. about Noon the Fleet got into the Channel, ſailing VVeſtward with all their Colours ſet out, and ſtretched in a Line betwixt <hi>Calais</hi> and <hi>Dover,</hi> ſo that it reached within a League of each Place. His Highneſs led the Van, attended by three Men of War; one at a diſtance before his Ship, and one on each ſide. The Tenders, as Pinks, Flyboats, and other Veſſels of this Kind, ſailed next, with their Decks throng'd with Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; the Flanks and Rear being guarded by the Men of VVar, but eſpecially the Rear, as being moſt in danger to be followed by the Engliſh Fleet. In this great Splendour and Order the whole Fleet ſailed with a Kind of Bravado betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> Drums beating, Colours flying, the Trumpets ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Hoboys playing, for the ſpace of three hours. Great was the Concourſe of Spectators on both Shores, at 20 miles diſtance from each other, to ſee this glorious Sight, worthy of the greateſt Monarch to behold. The Men of VVar that ſailed neareſt to <hi>Dover</hi> gave the Town and Caſtle ſome Guns, and thoſe that went on the other ſide did the ſame by <hi>Calais.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, conſiſting of about 34 Sail under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lord <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> lay then in the <hi>Buoy of the Nore;</hi> but did not think fit to ſtir, with a Number ſo much inferiour, and a parcel of Seamen who were Known to be VVell wiſhers to the Prince.</p>
               <p>The next Day, <hi>Nov.</hi> 4. being the Lord's Day, and the Day of the Prince's happy Birth and Marriage, the Fleet (being now come as far as the Iſle of <hi>VVight</hi>) obſerved the Duty of the Day; and did not Sail, but all were driven of the VVaves, till about four in the Afternoon. VVhen, the VVind being ſtill favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and blowing very freſh, every Ship made all the Sail ſhe could bear.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58818:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Torbay</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> was the Place intended for Landing. But the next Morning, <hi>Monday Nov.</hi> 5, proving very Hazy and Foggy, and full of Rain, the Fleet hapned to Sail beyond it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Nine of the Clock it cleared up; and, as Providence was pleaſed to order it, the VVind then choped about, and turned VVeſt South VVeſt, a moderate Gale. Which brought them back to <hi>Torbay,</hi> and having executed it's Commiſſion, was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately in another Corner.</p>
               <p>Then, by the Princes Order, the Standard was put up; the White Flag uppermoſt, ſignifying his Offer of Peace to all that would live Peaceably; and under that the Red (or Bloody) Flag, denouncing War to all ſuch as ſhould offer to oppoſe his juſt Deſigns.</p>
               <p>Of all this great Fleet, three Tenders only were intercepted by our Men of War. One of them a Fly-boat, having on Board four Companies of Foot of Colonel <hi>Babington</hi>'s Regiment, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Major <hi>Collambine.</hi> This was taken by Captain <hi>Aylmer,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Swallow</hi> Frigat. The other two, being a ſmall Pink and a Fiſhing Boat with 24 Horſe, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Fleet, were taken below <hi>Hole Haven</hi> by Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Haſtings,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Woolwich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Fleet landed at <hi>Torbay</hi> on the fifth of <hi>November.</hi> A memorable Day for the Gun-Powder Treaſon, which ſeems to have been marked out by Providence, that <hi>Englands</hi> Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Reign of <hi>James</hi> II. might begin the ſame Day that it was deſigned for Ruin and Deſtruction in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> I. The Year alſo is memorable; this Deliverance fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out in 88. juſt a hundred Years after <hi>England</hi> was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Invaſion in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, when it pleaſed God to confound and diſperſe that formidable Armada, which for its Greatneſs was in vain called <hi>Invincible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> being come into the Bay, with the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of the Floet, Boats were ordered to carry his Highneſs to Shore with his Gards, and the Noblemen that were about his Perſon. Who, being Landed, marched up the Hill, ſome before the Prince, and ſome after. Then the Guns fired from the Fleet, with the Beat of the Drums, the Sound of Trumpets, the Muſick of Hoboys, and the joyful Huzza's of the Fleet and Army; the Ships with all their Colours out, and the Colours of the Land-Forces that went out with the Prince, flying and <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58818:24"/>flouriſhing before his Highneſs. And, whilſt he was viewing the Ground on the Top of the Hill in order to In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Army, all hands in the Fleet were at work to carry the Men and Horſes, with their Neceſſaries, to Shore. So that the whole Army was Landed the next Day, being Tueſday, by three a Clock in the Afternoon; the Horſe being Landed firſt, and then the Foot. But their Cannon and Carriages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout for <hi>Topſham,</hi> and from thence brought up by Water to <hi>Exeter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the upper end of the Bay was a Fair Houſe belonging to one Mr. <hi>Carey</hi> a Papiſt, who entertained a Prieſt in his Houſe. This Prieſt having diſcovered the Fleet from the Leads of the Houſe, with the White Flags on ſome of the Men of War, concluded it to be the <hi>French</hi> Fleet come to Aſſiſt King <hi>James</hi> againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Tranſported with Joy at the Conceit of it, he without any more ado ordered all the Family to the Chappel, to ſing <hi>Te Deum</hi> for the Arrival of the <hi>French.</hi> But he was ſoon undeceived, and thererupon laughed at for his Religious Miſtake.</p>
               <p>This Houſe the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> upon his Landing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be Searched for Arms and Horſes. Some Horſes and a few Arms were found, and brought from thence; but without giving any further Diſturbance to the Houſe, where both the Searchers and the Searched entertained one another with mutual Civility.</p>
               <p>Near the Sea-ſide were ſome Thatched Houſes belonging to Fiſhermen, one of whom had the honour to Entertain the Prince at his Houſe, till the <hi>Wedneſday</hi> following. Which Day the Prince rode from this Place to Sir <hi>William Courtney</hi>'s, within a mile of <hi>Newton-Abbot,</hi> the firſt Market-Town; the firſt Line of the Army being about <hi>Newton,</hi> and the laſt upon their March thither. Here a Divine, going before the Army, went to the Croſs (or <hi>Town-Hall</hi>) on the Market-day; where he read aloud to the People the Prince's Declaration. Which ended with their joyful Acclamations, and kind Wiſhes to the Prince; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſoon after by Ringing of Bells, and Drinking of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce's Health. And, as his Highneſs was moſt kindly received and entertained at Sir <hi>VVilliam Courtney</hi>'s, ſo were the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers generally well treated by the Vulgar. Here began the <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58818:24"/>Provi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions to abound, which hitherto had been very ſcarce; and, as they were honeſtly paid for, ſo the Army was quickly ſupplyed with what the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntry could afford.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Thurſday Nov.</hi> 8th. the Lord <hi>Mordant</hi> (now Earl of <hi>Monmouth</hi>) came to <hi>Exeter</hi> with three or four Troops of Horſe, and Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> with him. But, when they came to one of the Gates, it was ſhut againſt them. Upon which the Lord <hi>Mordant</hi> commanded the Porter, on pain of Death, to open the Gate. Which being open, his Lordſhip commanded him on the ſame Pain, not to ſhut it again. My Lord and the Doctor went to the Mayor, to Know if he would meet the Prince at the Gate, and govern the City under Him. VVhich he excuſed, telling him he was under the Obligation of an Oath to His Majeſty, and therefore deſired the Prince would lay no Commands on him contrary to his Conſcience. Thus, after ſome Debate of the Matter, they parted; whilſt the Forces kept coming to Town.</p>
               <p>The next Day, being Friday <hi>Nov.</hi> 9th. the Prince came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Exeter,</hi> attended (beſides his Gards) with a brave Train of Nobles, Knights, and Gentlemen. Upon the Road he met with Multitudes of People, who welcomed His Highneſs with their Shouts and Huzza's. The ſame was done at <hi>Exeter,</hi> where the Streets were thronged on each ſide, the Windows beautified, and full of joyful Spectators. Being come to the Dean's Houſe, where He kept his Court, He took ſome Refreſhment; and then was pleas'd to go and render Thanks to God in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church, for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe Arrival. VVhere being ſat in the Biſhops Seat, then Abſent, the Quire began, and Sung <hi>Te Deum;</hi> and, after the Collects were ended, Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> Read the Prince's Declaration. Dr. <hi>Lamplugh,</hi> then Biſhop of this Dioceſs, was fled to <hi>London</hi> upon the Prince's Landing at <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay.</hi> VVhere having waited upon the King at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> His Majeſty was pleaſed to reward this piece of his Loyalty by Tranſlating him to the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>York,</hi> which had been a long time Vacant.</p>
               <p>The main Body of the Army marched in the mean time, the Horſe to the Neighbouring Pariſhes, and the Foot to <hi>Cliſt-Heath,</hi> where they Incamped. Both Horſe and Foot look'd very much Diſabled and Weather beaten, what with the Sea, and what with their March hither through bad Ways, and in Rainy <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58818:25"/>Weather, Their H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s were for the moſt part to Weak, that they could ſcarce ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d upon their Legs. So that, if the K ng's Forces had been read at han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, it might have gone very hard, in caſe o a Fight, with he Prince's Army. But it pleaſed God ſo to order it, that, while the King expected the Prince in the North, the Prince gave him the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>by, and took his Courſe a gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at way to the <hi>Weſt;</hi> that, being upon his Landing at a good diſtance from His Majeſties Forces, He might have time to Refreſh His own, before they could come to Action.</p>
               <p>The Prince therefore thought fit to ſtay a while at <hi>Exeter,</hi> but this was not the only Reaſon. Not a Perſon of Quality and Intereſt in thoſe Parts, (beſides Sir <hi>William Courtney,</hi>) had joyned Him hitherto, which His Highneſs did much wonder at. Only on the <hi>Monday, Nov.</hi> 12, one Captain <hi>Burrington</hi> came, and offered him his Service; who was accordingly very kindly received by His Highneſs. But, two Days after, ſeveral noted Gentlemen of <hi>Dorſet-Shire</hi> and <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> came in to Joyn the Prince, and waited on His Highneſs <hi>Thurſday Nov.</hi> 15 To whom He ſpoke after this manner.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <note place="margin">The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Speech to the Gentry that came to Joyn him at <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                              </note>Tho' We know not all your Perſons yet We have a Catalogue of your Names, and remember the Character of your Worth and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in your Country. You ſee We are come, according to your Invitation and our Promiſe. Our Duty to God obliges <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the Proteſtant Religion; and Our Love to Mankind, your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Properties. We expected you that dwell ſo near the Place of our Landing would have Joyned us ſooner. Not that it is now too late, nor that we want your Military Aſſiſtance, ſo much as your Countenance and Preſence, to juſtify our declared Pretenſions, in order to accompliſh our good and gracious Deſign. Tho' We have brought both a good Fleet and a good Army, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Kingdoms happy, by Reſcuing all Proteſtants from Popery, Slavery, and Arbitrary Power, by Reſtoring them to their Rights and Properties establiſhed by Law, and by Promoting of Peace and Trade, which is the Soul of Government and the Life of the Nation; yet we rely more on the goodneſs of God, and the Juſtice of our Cauſe, than on any humane Force and Power whatever. But, ſince God is pleaſed that we ſhould make uſe of humane Means, and not expect Miracles, for our Preſervation and Happineſs, let
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58818:25"/>us not neglect making uſe of this gracious Opportunity, but with Prudence and Courage put in execution our ſo honourable Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. Therefore Gentlement, Friends, and Fellow Protestants, We bid you and all your Followers moſt Heartily Welcome to our Court and Camp. Let the whole World now Judge, if our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions are not Juſt, Generous, Sincere, and above Price, ſince We might have even a Bridge of Gold to Return back. But it is our Principle and Reſolution rather to die in a good Cauſe, than live in a bad one; Virtue and true Honour being its own Reward, and the Happineſs of Mankind our great and only Deſign.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Both the Clergy and Gentry of this County were uneaſy, for fear that King <hi>James</hi> ſhould prevail, and therefore back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to declare for the Prince. But the People were forward enough. For, when the Drums beat for Volunteers, they came in apace from all Parts of the County, inſomuch that many Captains pickt and choſe their Souldiers. Thouſands did liſt themſelves to whom Arms were Given; and many more would have done the ſame, who were diſmiſſed, upon Mareſchal <hi>Schombergs</hi> Advice, that there was no need of them. Thus the Citizens Fears of King <hi>James</hi>'s Forces leſſening every day, they began to talk now more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to be more and more inclined towards the Prince. The Mayor himſelf and Aldermen, much taken up with their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations upon the preſent Juncture, came at laſt to viſit his Highneſs.</p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Lovelace</hi> coming through <hi>Cirenceſter</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> to joyn the Prince at <hi>Exeter</hi> with near
70 Horſe very well appointed, had the Misfortune to be ſtopt at that Town, and ſeized with thirteen of his Party, by the Officers of the Militia. Who met however with ſo ſharp a Reſiſtance, that ſeveral of them were killed, and others wounded. Amongſt the firſt were <hi>Lorege</hi> Major of the Regiment and his Son, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Lee</hi> a Deputy Lieutenant of the County, and <hi>Williams</hi> a Lieutenant.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time, <hi>viz.</hi> on <hi>Monday Nov.</hi> 12, the Lord <hi>Cornbury,</hi> Colonel of the Royal Regiment of Dragoons, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Salisbury,</hi> in order to bring over that Regiment, and two more of Horſe, to the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Which two Regiments of Horſe were the Royal Regiment, and the Duke <pb n="48" facs="tcp:58818:26"/>of S. <hi>Alban</hi>'s, then Commanded by Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton.</hi> They marched together, firſt to <hi>Dorceſter,</hi> where they refreſhed themſelves; and then went on to <hi>Bridport,</hi> and <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſter.</hi> Upon which ſeveral Officers, miſtruſting his Lordſhip, asked him whither they were going? Who anſwered, he had the King's Orders to beat up the Enemies Quarters at <hi>Honiton.</hi> But finding the Royal Regiment of Horſe, and ſeveral Officers of the Dragoons, did more and more ſuſpect him, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip marched with the Officers and Dragoons that would follow him towards <hi>Honiton,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Langſton</hi> marching before with the Regiment of S. <hi>Albans.</hi> As for the Royal Regiment of Horſe, and the reſt of the Dragoons, they march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back towards <hi>Bridport,</hi> being very much wearied by their long Marches, and put into ſome Diſorder by ſo great a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salisbury Plain</hi> was the Place of <hi>Rendez-vous</hi> for the Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, conſiſting of above 30000 Men, with a Great Train of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Feverſham;</hi> and all the Forces drew that Way, in order to a Battle.</p>
               <p>Mean while, to bring Things to an Accommodation, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Effuſion of Blood, a Petition for the Calling of a Free Parliament, Subſcribed by Nineteen Lord, both Spiritual and Temporal, was preſented to the King by the Lords Spiritual; <hi>viz.</hi> the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York</hi> Elect, the Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> in theſe Words.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="petition">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>May it pleaſe your Majeſty,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <note place="margin">The Lords Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                              <hi>We your Majeſties moſt Loyal Subjects, in a deep Senſe of the Miſeries of a War now breaking forth in the Bowels of this your Kingdom, and of the Danger to which Your Majeſties Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is thereby like to be expoſed, and alſo of the Diſtractions of your People by reaſon of their preſent Grievances, Do think our ſelves bound in Conſcience, of the 'Duty we ow to God, and our Holy Religion, to your Majeſty, and our Country, moſt humbly to offer to your Majeſty, That in our Opinion the only viſible Way to preſerve your Majeſty, and this your Kingdom, would be the Calling of a Parliament, Regular and Free in all its Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="49" facs="tcp:58818:26"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>We therefore do moſt earneſtly beſeech Your Majeſty, That You would be Graciouſly Pleaſed, with all Speed, to call ſuch a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; VVherein we ſhall be moſt ready to promote ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Reſolutions of Peace and Settlement in Church and State, as may conduce to Your Majeſties Honour and Safety, and to the Quieting of the Minds of Your People.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>VVe do likewiſe humbly beſeech Your Majeſty, in the mean time, to uſe ſuch Means for the preventing the Effuſion of Chriſtian Blood as to Your Majeſty ſhall ſeem moſt meet.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <closer>And Your Petitioners ſhall ever Pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The King's Anſwer.</note>To which the King gave this Anſwer. <hi>My Lords, VVhat you ask of Me I moſt paſſionately deſire; And I promiſe you,</hi> upon the Faith of a King, <hi>That I will have a Parliament, and ſuch an One as You ask for, as ſoon as ever the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>has quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Realm. For how is it poſſible a Parliament ſhould be Free in all its Circumſtances, as you Petition for, whilſt an Enemy is in the Kingdom, and can make a Return of near an hundred Voices?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the King's Pretence for ſhunning a Parliament. Which, being Regularly choſen, would in all probability call his evil Counſellors to an account, whom He thought himſelf bound in Honour to Protect; and ſtrictly Inquire into the Birth of the pretended Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> the Queſtioning of which was a Stab at his Heart. A Parliament that would probably bind up the Prerogative, pull down the Diſpenſing Power, and damn that Beaſt with Seven Heads, the Eccleſiaſtical Court. A Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament that would prove fatal to his dearly beloved Prieſts and Jeſuits, and that would have pulled down all their Schools and Chappels, had they not been prevented by the unaccountable Zeal of the Mobile. Laſtly, The King foreſaw, that the Prince would have demanded ſome Forts to be put into his Hands and the Parliaments, for their Security. So that He expected, in caſe of a Free Parliament, to be but a Nominal King, and an unhappy Inſtrument of the Ruin of his Child, Friends, and Religion. And, rather than do that, He choſe to Periſh.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, He might flatter himſelf with hopes, 1. That we ſhould never be able to Agree, after he had made it impoſſible for us to have a Legal Parliament. 2. That, when the Fear and Diſorder were over, the Church of <hi>England</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples would form a great Party for him in the Nation. 3. That the <hi>French</hi> King would Aſſiſt him with Forces and Mony; and, <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58818:27"/>if he ſhould prevail by Force, then by a Popiſh Army he would for ever Inſure the Slavery of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The only Advantage we could pretend to have by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with an Army was, to force the King to what he would never have yielded without that Force. And, had the Prince gone back <hi>Re infecta,</hi> 'tis not likely the King would have then granted us what he would not do now. Suppoſe he had called a Parliament, what Aſſurance could we have of their Sitting, as long as he ſhould have no Occaſion to Fear? Then, to be ſure, he would have disbanded the Proteſtants of his Army, and ſupply'd their rooms with <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, to have at laſt a Parliament (if a Parliament muſt be had) of their making.</p>
               <p>This being at that time the Poſture of our Affairs, that the Prince referred all to a Parliament, and the King would have none before he had quitted the Kingdom, all Things ſeemed diſpoſed to the Deciſion of a Bettel. In order to which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, accompanied by his Highneſs Prince <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> parted upon <hi>Saturday Nov.</hi> 17. from <hi>VVhite-hall</hi> for <hi>VVindſor,</hi> where he lay that Night; and the next Day continued his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to <hi>Salisbury,</hi> whither he came the
19th.</p>
               <p>About this time appeared a Letter from the Prince to the King's Army, in theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gentlemen and Friends,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Prince's Letter to the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Army.</note>
                        <hi>We have in Our Declaration given you ſo full and ſo true an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Our Intentions in this Expedition, that We cannot doubt but that all true</hi> Engliſhmen <hi>will come and concur with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s in our Deſtre to Secura theſe Nations from Popery and Slavery. We are come to Preſerve your Religion, and to Reſtore and Eſtabliſh your Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Properties. 'Tis plain, that you are only made uſe of as Inſtruments to Inſlave the Nation, and Ruin the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And, when that is done, you may judge what your ſelves ought to expect, both from the Caſhiering of all the Proteſtant Officers and Souldiers in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and by the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Souldiers being brought over to be put in your places. You know how many of your Fellow Officers have been uſed for their ſtanding firm to the Proteſtant Religion and to the Laws of</hi> England; <hi>and you cannot flatter your ſelves ſo far as to expect to be better uſed, if thoſe who have broke their VVord ſo <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58818:27"/>often ſhould by your means be brought out of thoſe Straits to which they are now reduced. VVe hope likewiſe, that you will not ſuffer your ſelves to be abuſed by a falſe Notion of Honour; but that you will in the firſt place conſider what you owe to Almighty God and your Religion, to your Country, to your Selves, and to your Poſterity, which You, as Men of Honour, ought to prefer to all private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations and Ingagements whatſoever. VVe do therefore expect, that you will conſider the Honour that is now ſet before you, of being the Inſtruments of Serving your Country, and Securing your Religion. And We will ever Remember the Service you ſhall do <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s upon this Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, by placing ſuch particular Marks of our Favour on every one of You as your Behaviour at this time ſhall deſerve of</hi> Us, <hi>in which VVe will make a great Diſtinction of thoſe that ſhall come ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to joyn their Arms with Ours. In ſhort, you ſhall find</hi> Us <hi>to be</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Well-wiſhing and Aſſured Friend, <hi>William Henry Prince of</hi> Orange.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Prince's Army began now to be in good heart, and one Man was as good as two when they came firſt to <hi>Exeter.</hi> Every day his Highneſs went out to view the Country with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal de <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and went once as far as <hi>Autry,</hi> 12 miles from <hi>Exeter.</hi> In the mean time Mr. <hi>Seymour</hi> was made Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and one Major <hi>Gibſon</hi> Deputy-Governour. For the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the Revenue here, the Lord <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> Mr. <hi>Herbord,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Row</hi> were appointed Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p>The Prince's Court began alſo to ſwell. For, beſides thoſe great Perſons which had attended his Highneſs from <hi>Holland</hi> hither, <hi>viz.</hi> Mareſchal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> Count <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> Count <hi>Solms,</hi> the Lords <hi>Zuleſtein, Bentick,</hi> and <hi>Overkirk;</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Earls or <hi>Shrewebury</hi> and <hi>Macclesfield,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Mordant,</hi> Lord <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> end Colonel <hi>Sidney,</hi> and of the <hi>Scotch</hi> the Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> with ſeveral other Perſons of Quality; here came to his Highneſs the Lord <hi>Cornbury,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Abington,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> beſides a great Number of Gentry. Who all entred together into an <hi>Aſſociation</hi> to Aſſiſt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in the Defence of the Proteſtant Religion, Laws, and Liberties of the People of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in theſe Words.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58818:28"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility at <hi>Exeter</hi> to ſtand by the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>We do Ingage to Almighty God, and to his Highneſs the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>and with one another, to ſtick firm to this Cauſe, and to one another in the Defence of it, and never to depart from it, until our Religion, Laws, and Liberties, are ſo far Secured to us in a Free Parliament, that We ſhall be no more in Danger of falling under Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Slavery. And, whereas we are ingaged in the Common Cauſe under the Protection of the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>by which means his Perſon may be expoſed to Danger, and to the deſperate and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Deſigns of Rapiſts, and other bloody Men, We do therefore ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly Ingage to God, and to one another, That, if any ſuch At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts be made upon Him, We will purſue not only thoſe that made them, but all their Adherents, and all We find in Arms againſt</hi> Us, <hi>with the utmoſt Severity of juſt Revenge in their Ruin and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that the Executing any ſuch Attempt (which God of his infinite Mercy forbid) ſhall not deprive</hi> Us <hi>from purſuing the Cauſe which We do now undertake, but that it ſhall Incourage us to carry it on with all the Vigour that ſo barbarbous an Approach ſhall do ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this ſtrict Aſſociation, the Prince ſaw how well theſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lords and Gentlemen were diſpoſed towards his Highneſs, and for the promoting the Good of the Common Cauſe.</p>
               <p>In the mean time he received Intelligence of the firſt Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh that hapned between the two Armies at <hi>Wincanton.</hi> To which Place a ſmall Party of Major General <hi>Mackay</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being advanced, to provide Carriage, Collonel <hi>Sarsfield</hi> having Notice of it marched thither with a Detachment of 70 Horſe, and 50 Dragoons and Granadiers, in order to cut them off. Who, hearing of <hi>Sarsfield</hi>'s Approach, reſolved upon a ſtout Defence, notwithſtanding their ſmall Number, being but 25. In order to which, <hi>Cambel</hi> their Lieutenant, poſted them in a ſmall Incloſure at the Eaſt end of the Town, where there was a good Hedge between them and the Road. Here they made a vigorous Defence, and ſeveral were killed and wounded on both ſides; when of a ſudden, upon a falſe Alarm of a ſtrong Party of the Prince's Horſe coming, <hi>Sarsfield</hi> and his Men retreated with all ſpeed, and in ſome diſorder. And, tho he had little Cauſe to boaſt of this Action, yet our <hi>Gazette</hi> did ſo magnifie it, that by it's Account of it 30 of the Prince's Men were kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of 25, beſides 6 taken, and 15 that made their eſcape.</p>
               <p>One would think, the King by this time had done with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations. <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58818:28"/>His Majeſty was two to one at leaſt as to the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Forces; and yet, to Ingroſs all to himſelf, he put out a Proclamation at <hi>Salisbury, Nov.</hi> 22. to Intice away all the Prince's Army, and ſo leave him by himſelf. By this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, firſt, <hi>He Offers and Grants his Pardon to all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that had taken up Arms with Foreigners and Strangers againſt Him and their Native Country; And next, to all ſuch Foreigners as ſhould come over to Him, promiſing either to Entertain them in his Service, or Grant them (if they ſhould deſire it) freedom of Paſſage, and liberty to Return to the Reſpective Countries from whence they came.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Stratagem would not do. And his Highneſs, having now received an Account of the Motions and Proceedings in the <hi>North</hi> for the Support of the Common Cauſe, prepared all Things for his March towards the King's Army. The Lords concerned in the <hi>North</hi> were the Earls of <hi>Devonſhire, Stamford,</hi> and <hi>Damby,</hi> the Lord <hi>Delamere,</hi> and others; who, being met at <hi>Nottingham</hi> with great Numbers of the Gentry, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Force of Horſemen well appointed, to repel all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, unanimouſly ſubſcribed to this Declaration, <hi>Nov.</hi> 23. the ſame Day that the King put out his Proclamation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Nobility, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at the Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous at <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>We the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonalty of theſe Northern Counties aſſembled together at</hi> Nottingham, <hi>for the Defence of our Laws, Religion, and Liberties, according to thoſe Free-born Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Priviledges deſcended to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s from our Anceſtors, as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubted Birth-right of the Subjects of this Kingdom of</hi> England <hi>(not doubting but the Infringers and Invaders of our Rights will Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent us to the reſt of the Nation in the moſt malicious Dreſs they can put upon us) do here <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimouſly think it our Duty to Declare to the reſt of our Proteſtant Fellow Subjects the Grounds of our preſent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are by innumerable Grievances made ſenſible, that the very Fundamentals of our Religion, Liberties, and Properties, are about to be Rooted out by our late Jeſuitical Privy Council, as has been of late too apparent.</hi> 1. <hi>By the King's Diſpenſing at his Pleaſure with all the Establiſhed Laws.</hi> 2. <hi>By Diſplacing all Officers out of all Offices of Truſt and Advantage, and Placing others in their Room that are Known Papiſts, deſervedly made Incapable by the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhed Laws of our Land.</hi> 3. <hi>By Deſtroying the Charters of moſt <pb n="54" facs="tcp:58818:29"/>Corporations in the Land.</hi> 4. <hi>By Diſcouraging all Perſons that are not Papiſts, preferring ſuch as turn to Popery.</hi> 5. <hi>By Diſplacing all honeſt and conſcientious Judges, unleſs they would, contrary to their Conſciences, declare that to be Law which was merely Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary.</hi> 6. <hi>By Branding all Men with the Name of Rebels, that but offered to juſtify the Laws in a Legal Courſe againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Proceedings of the King, or any of his corrupt Miniſters.</hi> 7. <hi>By Burdening the Nation with an Army, to maintain the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Rights of the Subjects.</hi> 8. <hi>By Diſcountenancing the Eſtabliſhed Reformed Religion.</hi> 9. <hi>By Forbidding the Subjects the Benefit of Petitioning, and conſtruing them Libeliers; ſo rendering the Laws a Noſe of Wax, to ſerve their Arbitrary Ends. And many more ſuch like, too long here to enumerate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We being thus made ſadly ſenſible of the Arbitrary and Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Government that is by the Influence of Jeſuitical Counſels com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon us, do <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimouſly Declare, That not being willing to deliver our Poſterity over to ſuch a Condition of Popery and Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as the aforeſaid Oppreſſions inevitably threaten, We will to the utmoſt of our Power Oppoſe the ſame, by Joyning with the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>whom we hope God Almighty has ſent to Reſcue us from the Oppreſſions aforeſaid, and will uſe our utmoſt Indeavours for the Recovery of our almoſt ruined Laws, Liberties, and Religion. Wherein we hope all good Proteſtant Subj cts will with their Lives and Fortunes be Aſſiſtant to us, and not be Bug-beared with the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Term of</hi> Rebels, <hi>by which they would fright us to become perfect Slaves to their Tyrannical Inſolencies and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations. For We aſſure our ſelves, that no rational and unbiaſſed Perſon will judge it Rebellion to Defend our Laws and Religion, which all our Princes have Sworn at their Coronation. Which Oath how well it has been obſerved of late We deſire a</hi> Free Parliament <hi>may have the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We own it Rebellion to Reſiſt a King that Governs by Law. But he was always accounted a Tyrant that made his Will the Law, and to Reſiſt ſuch a one we juſtly eſteem no Rebellion, but a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Defence. And in this Corſideration We doubt not of all honeſt Mons Aſſiſtance, humbly hoping for and imploring the great God's Protection, that turns the Hearts of the People as pleaſes him beſt. For it has been obſerved, that People can never be of one Mind without his Inſpiration; which has confirmed the Saying,</hi> Vox Populi Vox Dei.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58818:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The preſent Reſtoring of Charters, and Reverſing the oppreſſing and unjuſt Judgment given of</hi> Magdalen College <hi>Fellows, is plain, are but to ſtill the People,</hi> like Plums to Children, <hi>by deceiving them for a while. But, if they ſhall by this Stratagem be fooled, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll the preſent Storm that threatens the Papiſts be paſt, as ſoon as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſhall be Re-ſettled, the former Oppreſſion will be put on with greater Vigour. But we hope in vain is the Net ſpread in the ſight of the Birds. The Old Rule of Papiſts is ſo well known, that Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks, as they term Proteſtants, tho the Popiſh Religion is the greateſt Hereſy. 'Tis well known how ill Q.</hi> Mary <hi>obſerved her Promiſes to the</hi> Suffolk <hi>Men that helped her to the Throne. And how the Pope Diſpenſes with the Breach of Oaths, Treatiſes, or Promiſes, at his Pleaſure, when it makes for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Holy Church, as they term it. Theſe are ſuch convincing Reaſons to hinder <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s from giving Credit to the aforeſaid</hi> Mock-ſhews <hi>of Redreſs, that We think our ſelves bound in Conſcience to reſt on no Security that ſhall not be approved by a Freely Elected Parliament; to whom, under God, we Refer our Cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Declaration the Northern Commonalty, ſenſible of the Juſtice of it, and Influenced beſides by the Intereſt and Example of ſo many Lords and Gentlemen, did readily Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; and the <hi>Militia</hi> was Raiſed upon it, who gave a great Stroke towards the Revolution. For the News of it coming to the Kings Ears at <hi>Salisbury</hi> ſtruck ſuch a Damp upon his Spirits, that he began now to think his Caſe deſperate.</p>
               <p>To the ſame Effect was a Paper delivered from the Nobility and Gentry of the North by the Earl of <hi>Devonſhire</hi> to the Mayor of <hi>Darby,</hi> where his Lordſhip Quartered the 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>November;</hi> that is, <hi>for the Meeting and Sitting of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament freely and duly Choſen.</hi> With a declared Reſolution therein, <hi>That, in caſe any Interruption ſhould be given to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of a Parliament, they, the Nobility and Gentry of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Parts of</hi> England, <hi>would to their utmost Defend the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, the Laws of the Kingdom, and the Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> the Duke who bears that Title, found the Gentry and Common People in the ſame Diſpoſition. Being come to <hi>Lyn,</hi> attended by many of the Principal Men in the County, he received an Addreſs in the Market-place, preſented in theſe Words to his Grace by the Mayor, attended by the Body, and many hundreds of the Inhabitants.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:58818:30"/>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="speech">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <note place="margin">Addreſs of <hi>Lyn</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
                              </note>
                              <hi>The Daily Alarms we receive, as well from Foreign as Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Enemies, give us juſt Apprehenſions of the approaching Danger we conceive to be in; and make us apply our ſelves with all earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to your Grace, as our great Patron, that we may be put into ſuch poſture by your Directions and Conduct, as may make us appear as Zealous as any in the Defence of the Proteſtant Religion, the Laws, and Ancient Government of this Kingdom. Which is the Deſire of many Hundreds, who moſt humbly challenge a Right of your Graces Protection.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>To which his Grace was pleaſed to Anſwer thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="answer">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Mr. Mayor,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s Anſwer.</note>
                              <hi>I am very much obliged to You, and the reſt of your Body, and all here preſent, for your good Opinion of me, and the Confidence you have that I will do what in me lyes to ſupport and defend the Laws, Liberties, and Proteſtant Religion, in which I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deceive you. And, ſince the Coming of the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>has given us an Opportunity to Declare for the Defence of them, I can only aſſure you, that no Man will venture his Life and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune more freely for the ſame than I will do, eſpecially with all theſe Gentlemen here preſent, and many more of the ſame Principles. In order to which, you ſhall ſee all poſſible Care ſhall be taken to anſwer your Expectation.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Whereupon the <hi>Militia</hi> was ordered to be raiſed throughout the County. Which being thus put into a poſture of Defence, his Grace was pleaſed to deliver himſelf in theſe Words to the ſaid Corporation.</p>
                           <p>
                              <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi>'s ſecond Speech.</note>
                              <hi>I have indeavoured, as you ſee, to put you into the Poſture you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, by ſending both for Horſe and Foot of the Militia, and am very glad to ſee ſuch an Appearance of this Town in ſo good a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. I do again renew my former Aſſurances to you, that I will ever ſtand by you to defend the Laws, Liberties, and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion; and to procure a Settlement in Church and State, in concurrence with the Lords and Gentlemen in the North, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to the Declaration of the Prince of</hi> Orange. And ſo God Save the King.</p>
                           <p>In ſhort, the Genius of the whole Nation (if you except the Papiſts, and ſome falſe Proteſtants) did run that Way, and there was no ſtopping of ſo ſtrong a Current. Which his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was no ſooner ſatisfied in, but he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58818:30"/>marched from <hi>Exeter</hi> forward with his Army; the Fort of <hi>Plimouth</hi> being already Surrendred to his Highneſs by the Earl of <hi>Bath.</hi> At <hi>Exeter</hi> he only left a new raiſed Regiment to keep the City, under the Command of Sir <hi>John Guyes,</hi> then made Governour thereof.</p>
                           <p>The Army marching in three Lines, and the Prince in the ſecond Line, his Highneſs marched out from <hi>Exoter Nov.</hi> 22. and came to <hi>Crook-horn</hi> on <hi>Saturday</hi> 24. Then the Gentlemen of the Weſt came in apace, and joined him almoſt at every Stage. From <hi>Crook horn,</hi> where he ſtaid the 25th. he came the next Day to <hi>Sherborn,</hi> and lodged at the Caſtle; where the Duke of <hi>Grafton</hi> and the Lord <hi>Churchill,</hi> amongſt others, joyned him from the King's Army. Whereupon the Lord <hi>Churchill,</hi> who lay under particular Obligations to the King, wrote a Letter to his Majeſty in theſe following Terms.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Lord <hi>Churchills</hi> Letter to the King.</note>
                        <hi>Since Men are ſeldom ſuſpected of Sincerity, when they act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Intereſts; and, though my dutiful Behaviour to Your Majeſty in the worſt of Times (for which I acknowledge my poor Services much Over-paid) may not be ſufficient to Incline You to a charitable Interpretation of my Actions; Yet I hope, the great Advantage I injoy under Your Majeſty, which I can never expect in any other Change of Government, may reaſonably convince your Majeſty and the World, that I am acted by a higher Principle, when I offer that Violence to my Inclination and Intereſt, as to deſert Your Majeſty at a time when Your Affairs ſeem to challenge the ſtricteſt Obedience from all your Subjects, much more from One who lyes under the greateſt perſonal Obligations imaginable to Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. This, SIR, could proceed from nothing but the Inviolable Dictates of my</hi> Conſcience, <hi>and a neceſſary Concern for my</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>which no good Man can oppoſe, and with which I am inſtructed nothing ought to come in Competition. Heaven knows with what partiality my dutiful Opinion of Your Majeſty has hitherto repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Deſigns, which inconſiderate and ſelf-intereſted Men have framed againſt your Majeſties true Intereſt and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion. But, as I can no longer Joyn with ſuch to give a pretence by Conqueſt to bring them to effect, ſo will I always with the hazard of my Life and Fortune (ſo much your Majeſties Due) <pb n="58" facs="tcp:58818:31"/>indeavour to preſerve Your Royal Perſon and Lawful Rights, with all the tender concern and dutiful Reſpect that becomes,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Dutiful and moſt Obliged Subject and Servant, <hi>CHURCHILL.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>By this Deſertion the King grew more and more ſenſible how little he was to depend upon an Army, which daily mouldred away; Not for want of natural Affection to his Majeſty, but only to bring him off from his evil Counſellors, and into a neceſſity of Complying with the general Deſire of the Nation to have all Things Rectified by a Free and Legal Parliament</p>
               <p>Before the King left <hi>Salisbury,</hi> there hapned ſuch a ſudden Guſt of Wind as hurried down the Crown which had ſtood many Years upon the top of a Spire of the Cathedral. This was lookt upon as an ill Omen to the King. And ſo was his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties violent Bleeding at the Noſe, that could not be ſtopt for a long time any manner of way.</p>
               <p>The Vangards of both Armies being now near each other, a Party of the Prince's appeared not far from <hi>Salisbury.</hi> Upon which King <hi>James</hi> and his Army, thinking the Prince's whole Force were coming upon them, took the Alarm; ſo that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in the midſt of his Bleeding ordered his Coach forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be made ready, and drive away to <hi>Windſor.</hi> Upon whoſe Departure, his Forces in great haſte and diſorder march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſome one way, ſome another.</p>
               <p>The King being come to <hi>Andover,</hi> which was his firſt Stage homeward, his Royal Highneſs Prince <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> accompanied by his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Drumlangrig,</hi> withdrew from his Majeſty in the Night, in order to joyn the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at <hi>Sherborn;</hi> which they did the
29th. From whence Prince <hi>George</hi> ſent a moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Letter to the King, in theſe following Terms.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prince <hi>George</hi> his Letter to the King.</note>
                        <hi>With a Heart full of Grief I am forced to write what Prudence would not permit me to ſay to your Face. And way I ever find Credit with your Majeſty, and Protection from Heaven, as what I now do it free from Paſſion, Vanity, or Deſign. I am not ignorant of the frequent Miſchiefs wrought in the World by factious Pretences of Religion; but, were not Religion the moſt Juſtifiable Cauſe, it would not be made the moſt ſpecious Pretence. And Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty <pb n="59" facs="tcp:58818:31"/>has always ſhews too <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nintereſted a Senſe of Religion to doubt the juſt Effects of it in One whoſe Practices have (I hope) never given the World cauſe to cenſure his real Conviction of it, or his Backwardneſs to perform what his Honour and Conſcience prompt him to. I can therefore no longer diſguiſe my juſt Concern for that Religion in which I have been ſo happily Educated, which my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment throughly convinces me to be beſt, and for the Support of which I am ſo highly intereſted both in my Native Country and in this your Kingdom. Whilſt the reſtleſs Spirits of the Enemies of the Reformed Religion, backed by the cruel Zeal and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Power of <hi>France,</hi> juſtly alarm and unite all the Proteſtant Princes of Chriſtendom, and ingage them in ſo vaſt an Expence for the Support of it, can I act ſo degenerous and mean a part, as to deny my Concurrence to ſuch worthy Indeavours to diſabuſe Your Majeſty, by the Reinforcement of thoſe Laws, and Eſtabliſhing of that Government, on which alone depends the Well-being of your Majeſty, and of the Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Europe.</hi> This, SIR, is that irreſiſtible and only Cauſe that could come in Competition with my Duty and Obligations to your Majeſty, and be able to tear me from You, whilſt the ſame affectionate Deſire of Serving you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues in me. Could I ſecure your Perſon by the hazard of my Life, I ſhould think it could not be better imploy'd. And would to God theſe your distracted Kingdoms might yet receive that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory Compliance from your Majeſty in all their Juſtifiable Pretenſions, as might upon the only ſure Foundation, that of the Love and Intereſt of your Subjects, eſtabliſh your Government, and at ſtrongly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite the Hearts of all your Subjects to You as is that of</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                        <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Humble and moſt Obedient <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Servant.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This was a ſtrange Time for Flight. For, whilſt the King fled from <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> from the King, the Princeſs alſo took her Flight from the Cock-pit. Her Royal Highneſs, then big of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> not being able to bear the King's Diſpleaſure upon the Princes account or her own, withdrew her ſelf <hi>Nov.</hi> 26. early in the Morning, and went with the Ladies <hi>Churchill</hi> and <hi>Berkley,</hi> and the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> to the North, where the Forces were in Arms for the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Upon which her Royal Highneſs left a Letter for the Queen, in theſe following Words.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58818:32"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>MADAM,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> her Letter to the Queen.</note>I beg Your Pardon that I am ſo deeply affected with the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing News of the Prince's being gone, as not to be able to ſee Your Majeſty. However I leave this Paper to expreſs my humble Duty to the King and Your ſelf, and to let You know that I am gone to Abſent my ſelf to avoid the King's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure (which I am not able to bear) either againſt the Prince or my Self; intending to ſtay at ſo great a Diſtance, as not to Return, before I hear the happy News of a Reconcilen ent. And, as I am confident the Prince did not leave the King with any other Deſign, than to uſe all poſſible Means for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Preſervation; ſo I hope You will do me the Juſtice to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that I am uncapable of following him for any other End. Never was any one in ſuch an unhappy Condition, ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided between Duty to a Father and Affection to a Husband, that I know not what to do, but to follow One to preſerve the Other. I ſee the general Falling off of the Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who avow to have no other End than to prevail with the King to ſecure their Religion, which they ſaw ſo much in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by the violent Counſels of the Prieſts; who, to promote their own Religion, cared not to what Dangers they expoſed his Majeſty. I am fully perſuaded, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> deſigns the King's Safety and Preſervation, and hop all Things may be compoſed without more Blood-ſhed, by the Calling a Parliament. God grant a happy End to theſe Troubles, that the King's Reign may be proſpero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s, and that I may ſhortly meet You in perfect Peace and Safety. Till when, let me beg of You the Continuance of that favourable Opinion you have hitherto had of.</p>
                     </q>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Majeſties moſt obedient Daughter and Servant <hi>ANNE.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The ſame Day the Princeſs went, the King returned to <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> from <hi>Salisbury.</hi> Who, ſeeing how Things went, firſt tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sir <hi>Edward Hales</hi> out of his Government of the Tower, who being a Papiſt had threatned to Bomb the City; and made Colonel <hi>Bevile Skelton</hi> Lieutenant of the Tower, who had been a Priſoner there but a few Days before. Then his Majeſty gave Order to the Lord Chancellour to Iſſue out Writs for ſummoning a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to meet at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 15th. day of <hi>January</hi> next. Which was a great Step towards a Reconcilement, if ſo be the King had really intended it. But it proved a meer Amuſement. For his <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58818:32"/>Heart did beat for <hi>Verſailles;</hi> and the Pretence of a Parliament was only to poſſes the People with an Opinion, that he was reſolved to be Reconciled with them at any Rate, and in the mean time to Prepare himſelf under hand for a Retreat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nov.</hi> 30. He ſigned the Proclamation for the ſpeedy Calling of a Parliament, and ordered it with all ſpeed to be Publiſhed. Never was falſe Coin better plated, than this Proclamation was worded to amuſe the People. Theſe are the VVords.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>JAMES R.</signed>
                     </opener>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>We have thought fit, as the beſt and moſt proper Means to Eſtabliſh a laſting Peace to this Our Kingdom, to Call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;<note place="margin">The King's Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſpeedy Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and have therefore Ordered our Chancellour to cauſe Writs to be Iſſued forth for Summoning a Parliament, to Meet at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> upon the 15th. day of <hi>January</hi> next enſuing the Date of this Our Royal Proclamation. And, that nothing may be wanting on Our part towards the Freedom of Elections, as We have already Reſtored all Cities, Towns Corporate, and Boroughs throughout Our Kingdom, to their ancient Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Rights, and Priviledges; ſo we Require and Command all Perſons whatſoever, that they preſume not by Menace, or any other undue Means, to Influence Elections, or Procure the Vote of any Flector. And We do alſo ſtrictly Require and Command all Sheriffs, Mavors, Bailiffs, and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to whom the Execution or Return of any Writ, Summons, Warrant, or Precept, for Members to the inſuing Parliament ſhall belong, that they cauſe ſuch Writ, Summons, Warrant, and Precept, to be duly Publiſhed and Executed, and Returns thereupon to be fairly made, according to the true Merits of ſuch Elections.</p>
                        <p>And, for the Security of all Perſons both in their Election and Service in Parliament, We do hereby Publiſh and Declare, That all Our Subjects ſhall have free Liberty to Elect, and all Our Peers, and ſuch as ſhall be Elected Members of Our Houſe of Commons, ſhall have full Liberty and Freedom to Serve in Parliament, Notwithſtanding they have taken up Arms, or committed any Act of Hoſtility, or been any way Aiding or Aſſiſting therein. And, for the better Aſſurance hereof, We have Graciouſly directed a General Pardon to all Our Subjects, to be forthwith prepared to paſs Our Great Seal.</p>
                        <p>And, for the Reconciling all Publick Breaches, and Obliterat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very Memory of all paſt Miſcarriages, We do hereby
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58818:33"/>Exhort and Kindly Admoniſh all Our Subjects to diſpoſe themſelves to Elect ſuch Perſons for their Repreſentatives in Parliament as may not be Biaſſed by Prejudice or Paſſion, but Qualified with Parts, Experience, and Prudence, proper for this Conjuncture, and agreeable to the Ends and Purpoſes of this Our Gracious Proclamation.</p>
                     </q>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> having ſtaid ſome Days at <hi>Sherborn,</hi> moved towards <hi>Salisbury,</hi> by the VVay of <hi>Mere.</hi> At his Entrance into <hi>Salisbury,</hi> which was in great State, he was met by the Mayor and Aldermen in all their Formalities, the Bells ringing, the People ſhouting, and the whole City in a Tranſport of Joy at the ſight of their Deliverer. His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs rode into the City, with the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> at his right hand, and the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> on his left; and took up his Quarters at the Biſhop's Palace. Here his Highneſs made a Halt for ſome Days. VVhich the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> having notice of, ſhe came to <hi>Oxford,</hi> attended by a ſelect Troop of Country Gentlemen well Armed; where Prince <hi>George</hi> went to meet her Royal Highneſs.</p>
               <p>All the way the Army marched, Care was taken to diſperſe the Prince's Declaration; and where they hapned to Quarter upon <hi>Sundays,</hi> there it was read in the Churches. By this time the King's Army was much broken, moſt of the Proteſtant Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Souldiers come away, and Joyned his Highneſſes Forces. So that there was no Proſpect of a Field-Battel.</p>
               <p>After ſome Stay here the Prince came away, and marched to <hi>Amsbury,</hi> from thence to <hi>Collingburn,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Littlecot,</hi> where he came on <hi>Saturday Decemb.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the Lords Commiſſioners, <hi>viz.</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Hallifax,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphin,</hi> appointed by the King to treat with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> were come to <hi>Hungerford,</hi> being the Place agreed on for that purpoſe by the Prince. To whom a VVriting, ſubſcribed by their Lordſhips, was delivered in theſe following VVords.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>The King has commanded us to acquaint you, That he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth all the Differences and Cauſes of Complaint alledged by your Highneſs ſeem to be Referred to a Free Parliament. His Majeſty, as he has already declared, was reſolved before to Call one, but thought that in the preſent State of Affairs it was Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58818:33"/>to Defer it, till Things were more compoſed. Yet, ſeeing that his People ſtill continued to deſire it, he hath put forth his Proclamation in order to it, and has iſſued forth his Writ, for Calling of it. And, to prevent any Cauſe of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in it, he will conſent to every Thing that can be reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably required for the Security of all thoſe that ſhall come to it. His Majeſty has therefore ſent us to attend your Highneſs, for the Adjuſting of all Matters that ſhall be agreed to, neceſſary for the Freedom of Elections, and the Security of Sitting; and is ready immediately to enter into a Treaty, in order to it. His Majeſty propoſeth, that in the mean time the reſpective Armies may be Reſtrained within ſuch Limits, and at ſuch Diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> as may prevent the Apprehenſions that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament may in any Kind be Diſturbed; being deſirous, that the Meeting of it may be no longer Delay'd than it muſt be by the uſual and neceſſary Forms.</p>
                     </q>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>In Anſwer to which, theſe following Propoſals were made by the Prince, with the Advice of the Lords and Gentlemen Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled with his Highneſs.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<q rend="margQuotes">That all Papiſts, and ſuch Perſons as were not Qualified by Law, ſhould be Diſarmed, Disbanded, and Removed from all Imployments, Civil and Military. 2. That all Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which Reflected upon his Highneſs, or any that was come over to him, or had declared for him, ſhould be Recalled; and, if any Perſons, for ſo doing, had been Committed, they ſhould be forthwith ſet at Liberty. 3. That, for the Security and Safety of the City of <hi>London,</hi> the Cuſtody and Government of the Tower be immediately put into the hands of the ſaid City.
4. That, if his Majeſty ſhall think to be at <hi>London</hi> during the Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Parliament, his Highneſs might be there alſo, with equal Number of Gards. Or, if his Majeſty ſhould rather chuſe to be in any Place from <hi>London,</hi> his Highneſs might be at a Place of the ſame Diſtance. 5. That the Reſpective Armies ſhould Remove 30 Miles from <hi>London,</hi> and no more Foreign Forces ſhould be brought into the Kingdom. 6. That, for the Security of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and their Trade, <hi>Tilbury-Fort</hi> be put into the hands of the ſaid City. 7. That to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Landing of <hi>French,</hi> or other Foreign Troops, <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> be put into ſuch hands as by the King and Prince ſhould be agreed upon. 8. That ſome ſufficient Part of the Publick
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58818:34"/>Revenue be aſſigned his Highneſs, for the Maintaining of his Forces till the Meeting of the Parliament.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The King, upon the View of theſe Propoſals, Reſolved upon a ſpeedy Retreat into <hi>France.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> ſo called was ſent for before-hand to go thither along with the Queen, who accordingly ſet out <hi>December</hi> 10. And the next Day, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Morning, the King, attended by Sir <hi>Edward Hales,</hi> went away from <hi>White-kall Incognito.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before his Departure he ſent Notice of it to the Earl of <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham,</hi> by a Letter framed in theſe Words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <p>Things being come to that Extremity, that I have been forced to ſend away the Queen and my Son the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> that they might not fall into my Enemies hands (which they muſt have done, if they had ſtaid.) I am obliged to do the ſame Thing and to indeavour to Secure my ſelf the beſt I can, in hopes it will pleaſe God out of his infinite Mercy to this unhappy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to touch their hearts again with true Loyalty and Honour. If I could have relyed on all my Troops, I might not have been put to the Extremity I am in, and would at leaſt have had one Blow for it. But, tho I know there are many loyal and brave Men amongſt you both Officers and Souldiers, yet you know that both your Self and ſeveral of the General Officers, and others of the Army, told me, it was no ways adviſable for me to venture my ſelf at their Head, or think to fight the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with them. What remains is only for me to Thank you, and all thoſe both Officers and Souldiers who have ſtuck to Me, and been truly Loyal; not doubting in the leaſt but that you will ſtill retain the ſame Fidelity to Me. And, tho I do not expect you ſhould expoſe your ſelves by Reſiſting a Foreign Army, and a <hi>Poiſoned</hi> Nation; yet I hope your former Principles are ſo inrooted in You, that you will keep your ſelves free from Aſſociations, and ſuch pernicious Things. Time preſſes ſo that I can ſay no more.</p>
                     </q>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>J. R.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> upon the Receipt of the Letter, immediately diſpatched a Meſſenger to the Prince, to let him know, <hi>That, having received a, Letter from the King with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfortunate News of his Going out of</hi> England, <hi>and his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtics Order</hi> (as he expreſſes it) <hi>to make no Oppoſition againſt <pb n="65" facs="tcp:58818:34"/>any body, he thought himſelf obliged to acquaint his Highneſs with it as ſoon as it was poſſible, to prevent Effuſion of Blood; To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he had given the laſt Order to all the Troops that were under his Command.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before the King's Departure, ſeveral Papiſts foreſeeing the Revolution, had withdrawn themſelves beyond Sea. Now the Prieſts and Jeſuites, who expected no Quarter, began to ſhift for themſelves, and run ſome one Way, ſome another. Thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Proteſtants who were the moſt Obnoxious, and had ſo baſely comply'd with the Times, were alſo put to their Shifts. Some of both ſorts were Apprehended; but moſt made their Eſcape, or lay Undiſcovered. The Lord Chancellor <hi>Jeffreys,</hi> a <hi>Mezzo-tinto</hi> Proteſtant, as forward as any Papiſt to Comply with King <hi>James</hi>'s Deſigns, was taken in a Diſguiſe at <hi>Wapping Dec.</hi> 12. and committed to the Tower; where he pined away, and died ſome time after. The Earl of <hi>Peterborough</hi> being ſecured in <hi>Kent,</hi> as he was making his Eſcape, was alſo ſent to the Tower.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the Disbanded Army diſperſed it ſelf up and down the City and Country in an unuſual and unwarrantable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to the great Diſturbance of the Publick Peace and Quiet. The Mobile on the other ſide, taking an Advantage of this State of Anarchy, fell to work, by burning, pulling down, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe defacing ſeveral Houſes and publick Buildings of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, rifling and plundering the ſame. And, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Regard to the Character of Embaſſadours, they pulled down and plundered the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Embaſſadors Houſe; whoſe Damages were afterwards abundantly made up by the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus King <hi>James</hi> leſt his Party to the Mercy of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whoſe unaccountable Outrages and Violences could not be prevented in that critical Time. Yet their Rage fell much ſhort of what the Papiſts expected, conſidering their former Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for I could not hear of any Hurt they did to their Perſons. Whereas the major Part of them expected nothing leſs than Death and Deſtruction; as it had been our Fate, had our Caſe been their own. Which piece of Moderation from a looſe, provoked, and mighty Rabble, without the Reſtraint of any Government, is not to be parallel'd in Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>As for the falſe Alarm which hapned upon it of the deſperate Iriſh Forces Burning and Plundering, and putting to the Sword all they met in their Way, as Improbable as the Thing was in it ſelf, yet it got ſuch
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58818:35"/>Credit all over the Kingdom, that the whole Nation was in a ferment upon it, and all the Militia in Arms to oppoſe the pretended Fury of a ſort of Men, which the Sound of a Horn had newly put to Flight at <hi>Reading,</hi> and that of an old Barrel at <hi>Maidenhead.</hi> But, however the Alarm was given, it was not without ſome Deſign; and, whatever was in the Top, one might eaſily gueſs, that Policy was in the Bottom. For, to imagine that four or five thouſand <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhould all of a ſudden be grown ſo Deſperate as to think to <hi>Post away</hi> this Nation with Fire and Sword, when the very ſight of a leſs Number of reſolute Men might have made them ſhew their Heels, was a Thing fitter to laugh at than to be concerned for.</p>
               <p>One Thing is Obſervable in the King's Deſertion, <hi>viz.</hi> the Great Seals be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt into the <hi>Thames,</hi> as it was found out afterwards. Which lookt like a wilful Deſertion of the Government, and an intire Abdication thereof. At leaſt he ſeemed thereby to imply, that, in caſe he ſhould Return, he was reſolved not to Rule by Law, of which the Great Seal ſeems always to carry ſome Prints.</p>
               <p>King <hi>James</hi> being thus gone, not able to bear the brunt of a Parliament, and the Writs prepared for it being ſtopt, made his Way by Water for <hi>France</hi> with all ſpeed; till he hapned to be ſtopt at <hi>Feverſham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> as we ſhall ſee afterwards.</p>
               <p>Upon the News of his being Gone, there was a Meeting that very Day at <hi>Guild-hall</hi> of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in and about the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to the Number of nine and twenty; who agreed upon, and ſigned a Declaration. In which, having firſt expreſſed their Zealous Concern for the Nation in this dangerous Conjuncture, upon the King's having Withdrawn himſelf in order to his Departure out of this Kingdom, they Unanimouſly Declared <hi>their Reſolution to apply themſelves to His Highneſs the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>and to Aſſiſt him with their utmoſt Indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in the ſpeedy Obtaining of a Parliament, whereby our Laws, Liberties, and Properties might be Secured; the Church of</hi> England <hi>in particular, with a due Liberty to Proteſtant Diſſenters, and in general the Proteſtant Religion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt over the whole World might be Supported and Incouraged.</hi> They further Declared, <hi>That in the mean time they would Indeavour to Preſerve, to the utmoſt of their Power, the Peace and Security of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and the Parts adjacent; And, if any Thing more could be performed by Them, for promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing His Highneſſes generous Intentions for the Publick Good, that they would be ready to do it, as Occaſion ſhould require.</hi> With which Declaration four of their Body, <hi>Viz.</hi> the Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> the Lord Viſcount <hi>Wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Culpeper,</hi> were deſired to attend His Highneſs. Which they did accordingly.</p>
               <p>The ſame day two Addreſſes were Agreed upon, one from the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and the Commons of the City of <hi>London</hi> in the Common Council Aſſembled, and another from the Lieutenancy of <hi>London;</hi> which were both preſented to his Highneſs at <hi>Henly</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire, Dec.</hi> 13. with the Lords Declaration. Which Addreſſes, in ſhort, contained <hi>Their humble Acknowledgment of His Highneſſes fervent Zeal for the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nparalled Generoſity in Expoſing his Perſon to ſo many
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58818:35"/>Dangers both by Sea and Land, to Reſcue theſe Nations from Slavery and Popery;</hi> With a Declaration, <hi>that they preſumed to make his Highneſs their Refuge, and therefore begged his Protection.</hi> And at laſt humbly beſeeching his Highneſs <hi>to Repair with all convenient Speed to the Capital City, for the perfecting the great Work He had ſo happily begun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince, having now a certain Account of the King's being gone away, did put out a Declaration, <hi>Requiring all colonels and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in Chief of the Regiments, Troops, and Companies of the Royal Army that had Diſperſed themſelves, to call together by Beat of Drum, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the ſeveral Officers and Souldiers belonging to their reſpective Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Troops, and Companies, in ſuch Places as they ſhould find moſt convenient for their Rendez-vous, and there to keep them in good Order and Diſcipline; And all ſuch Officers and Souldiers forthwith to Repair to ſuch Places as ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpoſe by their reſpective Colonels and Commanders in Chief; whereof His Highneſs required ſpeedy Notice to be given unto Him, for his further Orders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King in the mean time, who was ſuppoſed to be near the Coaſt of <hi>France.</hi> was unluckily ſtopt in a Smack nigh <hi>Feverſham</hi> by ſome ſturdy Fellows then Jeſuite-hunting; and was Secured for One, till he came to be Known. Then he was prevailed upon to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>White-hall,</hi> which he did on the 16th. Where being Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of divers Outrages and Diſorders that had been committed in his Abſence, He was pleaſed that very Night in Council to give Orders <hi>for the preventing all ſuch Outrages and Diſorders for the future.</hi> Which proved the laſt Publick Act of his Regal Power.</p>
               <p>His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was now come to <hi>Windſor,</hi> where he ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on Friday <hi>Dec.</hi> 14. From whence he had ſent the Sieur <hi>de Zuleſtein</hi> to the King, who likewiſe ſent the Earl of <hi>Feverſham</hi> to his Highneſs to Invite him to S. <hi>James</hi>'s. But his Lordſhip was ſecured in the Caſtle, by the Prince's Order, for his late Irregular Disbanding of the King's Forces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 17. In the Night the King's Gards were changed by the Prince's, then arrived at S. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park.</hi> Which Proceeding the <hi>Jacobites</hi> do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt as a great piece of Iniquity, and look upon as unaccountable. But, as the Caſe ſtood, the Thing was unavoidable; and, as I am apt to think the King's Invitation was none of the more Cordial, ſo I preſume this Proceeding of the Prince was not free from Reluctancy. Upon the King's Going off, the Lords Aſſembled at <hi>Guild hall,</hi> and the City, had put themſelves under the Prince's Protection, as being left in a State of Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; and his Highneſs had now the Command of the King's Forces, ſo that it was in his power to order them as he thought moſt ſutable to the preſent Juncture. Therefore it did not any way conſiſt with his Honour to ſuffer this part of the ſaid Forces to act independently from him in ſo critical a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Time, which might have occaſioned a general Diſturbance and Breach of the Peace, the Keeping whereof was the principal Care of his Highneſs. Who clapt his Gards upon the King, not out of any Deſign upon his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but rather to Secure him from any Attempts of a rude and incenſed Rabble I would fain know what Harm befell him from this Change. It appears on the contrary by what follows, that, notwithſtanding theſe <hi>Dutch</hi> 
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58818:36"/>Gards, the King might diſpoſe of himſelf as he pleaſed. 'Tis for this the Lord without Doors clamoured and kept a heavy Splutter in his Speech to the Houſe of Lords. Wherein, under pretence that the King was not gone out of his Territories, and that he might be where he would in his own Kingdom, he concludes there was no Deſertion in the Caſe. But this is perfect Shuffling. 'Tis well known, that, if he had ſtaid, a Parliament muſt be had, and that he dreaded nothing more than a Parliament that would rake up old Sores, and find out who made them. 'Tis well known, that his Heart panted after the Queen, and that he had no Buſineſs at <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſham.</hi> The Time and Manner of his Setting out are a plain Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that he was quitting a Kingdom, which was now grown Uneaſy to him; and his Caſting the Great Seal into the <hi>Thames,</hi> adds much to the Argument. Had he but weathered the Point, and got clear off out of the River, 'tis ten to one that he had not been put to the trouble of a ſecond Flight.</p>
               <p>In order to which, ſeeing now his Caſe deſperate, and the Prince at his Heels, he went about Noon from <hi>White-hall Dec.</hi> 18. to Sir <hi>Richard Head</hi>'s nigh <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> ſtill ſteering his Courſe towards <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That very Day his Highneſs parted from <hi>Windſor,</hi> dined at <hi>Sion-Houſe,</hi> and came in the Evening to S. <hi>James</hi>'s. Where he received the Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of all the Nobility, and other Perſons of the chiefeſt Quality in Town; And at Night the Streets were filled with Boneſires, with Ringing of Bells, and other Publick Demonſtrations of Joy.</p>
               <p>The next Day, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 19. Their Royal Highneſſes Prince <hi>George</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> returned from <hi>Oxford</hi> to the Cock-pit; where They were preſently after Viſited by his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Who that Afternoon went alſo to Viſit the Queen Dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at <hi>Somerſet-Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20. The Lord Mayor (Sir <hi>John Chapman</hi>) being indiſpoſed, the Aldermen and their Deputies, with ſome of the Common Council of each Ward, by Order of the Common Council, Waited on the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to Congratulate his Highneſs on his happy Arrival at S. <hi>James</hi>'s. Which was performed by Sir <hi>George Treby</hi> the Recorder in an Eloquent Speech, and very favourably received by his Highneſs. The Speech was thus.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it pleaſe Your Highneſs,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Sir <hi>George Treby</hi> his Speech from the City to the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                        </note>The Lord Mayor being Diſabled by Sickneſs, Your Highneſs is attended by the Aldermen and Commons of the Capital City of this Kingdom, deputed to congratulate Your Highneſs upon this great and glorious Occaſion. In which We cannot but come ſhort in Expreſſion. Reviewing our late Danger, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our Church and State over-run by Popery and Arbitrary Power, and even brought to the Point of Deſtruction, by the Conduct of ſome Men (our true Invaders) who brake the Sacred Fences of our Laws, and (which was worſt) the very Conſtitution of our Legiſlature. So that there was no Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy left but the laſt. The only Perſon, under Heaven, that could apply this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, was Your Highneſs. You are of a Nation, whoſe Alliance in all Times has been agreeable and proſperous to us. You are of a Family moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Benefactors to Mankind. To have the Title of Soveraign Prince, and <hi>Stadtholder,</hi> and to have worn the Imperial Crown, are among their leſſer <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58818:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>Dignities. They have long injoyed a Dignity ſingular and tranſcendent, <hi>viz.</hi> To be Champions of Almighty God, ſent forth in ſeveral Ages, to Vindicate his Cauſe againſt the greateſt Opreſſions. To this Divine Commiſſion our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, our Gentry, and among them our brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> Souldiers, rendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Arms upon your Appearing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>GREAT SIR,</hi> when we look back to the last Month, and contemplate the Swiftneſs and Fulneſs of our preſent Deliverance, aſtoniſhed, we think it Miraculous. Your Highneſs, led by the Hand of Heaven, and called by the Voice of the People, has preſerved our greateſt Intereſts. The Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is Primitive Chriſtianity reſtored. Our Laws, which are our ancient Title to our Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates, and without which this World were a Wild<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rneſs. But what Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ribution can we make to Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Our Thoughts are full charged with Gratitude. Your Highneſs has a laſting Monument in the Hearts, in the Prayers, in the Praiſes of all good Men amongst us. And late Poſterity will celebrate your ever glorious Name, till Time ſhall be no more.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> publiſhed an Order for Returning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Publick Store the Arms of divers Souldiers that were loſt or imbezelled, ſince the Disbanding of the Royal Army. At the ſame time he appointed Quarters for the <hi>Engliſh, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces, to which all Officers and Souldiers belonging thereto were ordered forthwith to Repair.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 23. Was the Day when the King, notwithſtanding his <hi>Dutch</hi> Gards about him, made ſhift to give them the ſlip. So that he got ſafe into <hi>France,</hi> where the Queen was arrived before with the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> Thus he left us again in an unſetled Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; But Care was taken to ſecure the Peace.</p>
               <p>In this Condition, had the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had any Deſign to take the Government upon him, this was the Time. He was now come to the Capital City of the Kingdom, through a perpetual Croud of Applauſes and Benedictions, and had the Hearts of all true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants. Being a Prince of the Royal Blood that ſtood ſo near to the Immediate Succeſſion, and having beſides a good Army with him, he had nothing to do but what he might eaſily have done; that is, to make a Party to ſupport his Intereſt, and withſtand all Oppoſition. The Law it ſelf could have afforded him a Claim, it being an undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Maxim among Lawyers, That the Succeſs of a Juſt War gives a Lawful Title to that which is acquired in the Progreſs of it And (as the Learned Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> ſays in his Paſtoral Letter) if at Common Law an Heir in Remainder has juſt Cauſe to Sue him that is in Poſſeſſion, if he makes Waſts on the Inheritance which is his in Reverſion, much more ought the Heir of the Crown to Interpoſe, when he ſees him that is in Poſſeſſion hurried on blind-fold to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject an Independent Kingdom to a Foreign Juriſdiction, and thereby to Rob it of it's Glory and Security. Eſpecially when 'tis plain, this muſt occaſion the greateſt Ruin and Miſeries poſſible to that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and when a pretended Heir was ſet up in ſuch a manner, that the whole Kingdom believed it Spurious. In ſuch a Caſe it cannot be denied, even according to the higheſt Principles of Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58818:37"/>that another Sovereign Prince might make War on a King ſo abuſing his Power; and that this was the Caſe in Fact, will not be called in queſtion by any Proteſtant, Therefore King <hi>James,</hi> having ſo far ſunk in the War, that he both abandoned his People and deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Government, all his Right and Title did accrue to the Prince in the Right of a conqueſt over him. So that, if he had then aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Crown, the Opinion of all Lawyers muſt have been on his ſide. And which Way ſoever King <hi>James</hi>'s Deſerting the Government be turned, this Argument has much Weight. For, if he was forced to it, then here was a Conqueſt; and, if it was voluntary, it was a wilful D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſertion.</p>
               <p>But, whatever Proſpect His Highneſs might have of a Crown, either by the Sword, or the Law, or both Ways together, He choſe rather to leave the Matter to the Determination of the Peers and People of <hi>England,</hi> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and Aſſembled together with all poſſible Freedom.</p>
               <p>Mean while, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal Aſſembled <hi>December</hi> 25. in the Houſe of Lords at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and at the ſame time the Members of the Parliaments that had ſerved during the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> 2d. met in the Houſe of Commons, together with the Court of Aldermen and Common-Council of <hi>London.</hi> Who unanimouſly Agreed upon a general <hi>Convention</hi> of the Lords and Commons to Meet on the 22. of <hi>Jan.</hi> next; and pray'd his Highneſs in the mean time to take upon him the Adminiſtration of Publick Affairs, both Civil and Military, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of the Publick Revenues, till the Meeting of the ſaid Convention. In Order to which Meeting, He ſent at their Requeſt, and according to their Directions, His Letters throughout the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Then came out two D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clarations from His Highneſs, One for Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing Sheriffs, Juſtices of the Peace, and other Officers and Miniſters (not Papiſts) that were in Office upon the firſt day of <hi>December,</hi> to Act in their reſpective Places. Another, for the better Collecting the Publick Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. Beſides an Order, for carrying on the Elections for the intended Convention with greater Freedom, and without any Colour of Force or Reſtraint. His Highneſs alſo took a convenient Care to Reſtrain the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs of the Preſs within the bounds of the Law. Then He put forth a Declaration, for the better Quartering of the Forces. Another to Incourage the Sea-men of the Fleet, then labouring under Diſcontents, and abſenting themſelves, upon ſeveral untrue and groundleſs Reports Maliciouſly ſpread among them, and to warn them at their Peril to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their Duty. A third, to the ſame purpoſe, for the Land Forces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jaruary</hi> 22. being the day appointed for the Convention to meet at <hi>Wes;tminſter,</hi> there they met accordingly. Where the two Speakers being choſen, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord Marquis of <hi>Halliface</hi> for the Houſe of Lords, and <hi>Henry Powle</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> for the Commons, a Letter from the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was read in both Houſes, to this effect; <hi>That he had endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what was deſired from Him for the Publick Peace and ſafety during his Adminiſtration; and that it now lay on them to lay a Foundation of a firm Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for their Religion, Laws, and Liberties; That he did not doubt but by <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58818:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch a full and Fret Repreſentative of the Nation, the Ends of his Declaration would be attained.</hi> He recommended to them <hi>the dangerous Condition of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and alſo the States of</hi> Holland, <hi>both which required large and ſpee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly Succours; And to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d them that, ſince it had pleaſed God hitherto to bleſs his good Lite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tions with ſo great Succeſs, be tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſled in him, that he would complete his own Work, by ſending a Spirit of Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence their Courſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, that ſo no I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>terruption might be given to a happy and laſting Settlement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon the Lords and Commons unanimouſly reſolved upon an Addreſs to be preſented to his Highneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hanks for what he had done, and humbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to deſire him to continue the Adminiſtration of Publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, till farther Application were made by them to his Highneſs. A Day of Publick Thankſgiving to Almighty God was likewiſe appointed by both Houſes, for having made his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Inſtrument of the great Deliverance of this Kingdom from Popery and Arbitrary Power. And then the Lords and Commons went in a Body to St. <hi>James</hi>'s, to preſent the fore-mentioned Addreſs to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>The State we were in required a ſpeedy Settling of the Government on ſure and lafting Foundations; and conſequently, that ſuch Perſon or Perſons ſhould be immediately placed in the Throne, in whom the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had moſt reaſon to repoſe an intire Confidence. It therefore now lay upon the Convention to Make ſo Judicious a Choice, as in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability might render us a happy People, and give our Poſterity cauſe to Rejoyce, when they ſhall read the Proceedings of this Wiſe and Grand Convention.</p>
               <p>'Tis obſerved that, before the Theocracy of the Jews ceaſed, even in the time of extraordinary Revelations, the manner of the Divine Deſignation of their Judges was by God's giving the People ſome Deliverance by the Hand of the Perſon, to whoſe Government they were appointed to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. Thus <hi>Othniel, Gideon, Jephthab, Samſon,</hi> and others, were inveſted by Heaven with the ſupream Authority. And, tho' <hi>Joſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> had an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Command from God to ſucceed <hi>Moſes,</hi> and an Anointing for that purpoſe by the laying on of <hi>Moſes</hi> hands; yet the Foundation of the Peoples Submiſſion to him was laid in <hi>Jora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> Now what Hiſtory can give an Inſtance, ſince that Theocracy ceaſed, of a Deſignation of any Perſon to any Government more viſibly Divine than this was? To ſee a Nation of ſo various Opinions, Intereſts, and Factions fall ſuddenly from a turbulent and fluctuating State into a ſerene Calm, and their Minds ſo ſtrangely united on a ſudden, it ſhews from whence the Nation was Influenced. And whoever conſiders how the Poſture of Foreign Affairs, which no humane Wiſdom or Power could have brought about, made way for this Expedition; how the Prince's Counſels were all along di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and crowned with Succeſs, amongſt ſo many Dangers and Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and that in ſo little time, and with ſo little Effuſion of Blood, muſt needs ſee plainly the Finger of God in all this, pointing out to us what choice we were to make.</p>
               <p>Yet various were the Projects amongſt the Members of the Convention. Some were for Sending to the King, and Treating with him to Return, but <pb n="72" facs="tcp:58818:38"/>under ſuch Reſtraints as they thought ſhould diſable him from Invading our Laws, Religion, and Liberties. But what reſtraint could be put upon a King who was under a Vow of Reſtoring Popery? The Kingly Power (one would think) was ſufficiently limited by the Law, ſo as to preſerve the Religion and Liberties of the People, under the Glory and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a King. But the Experince of King <hi>James</hi> his Reign ſhewed us ſufficiently, how eaſy it was for a King to break through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence of the Laws, and that they were but Cobwebs to a Prince whoſe Zeal or Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could not indure any Bounds. What Ways could be found out, ſo to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye up his Hands as to Secure his Subjects, but ſuch as muſt make him a meer Titular King; which had been a greater Affront put upon Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, than downright Depoſing of him? He therefore choſe rather to quit the Crown, than be turned from the ſweet Exerciſe of an Abſolute Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the State of a Baby King, to be turned and wound by his Subjects as they pleaſed, to obſerve their Dictates, and ſubmit to their Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Some were for making the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> Regent; Others, the Prince. Some again were for declaring the Crown forfeited or demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and proclaiming only the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> Queen; Others, for making the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> only King.</p>
               <p>But the Plurality carryed it, firſt for having the Government Diſſolved, then making the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> joyntly King and Queen of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. The publick Acts to run in the Name of Both; but the Executive Power to be ſolely in the King.</p>
               <p>Thus King <hi>James</hi> II. for having indeavoured to Subvert the Conſtitution of the Kingdom by breaking the Original Contract between King and People, and by Advice of Jeſuites and other wicked Perſons Violated the Fundamental Laws, and having at laſt Withdrawn himſelf out of this Kingdom, was Voted by the Houſe of Commons, <hi>to have Abdicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Government, and the Throne to be Vatant.</hi> And, after ſeveral Days Debates about it, the Houſe of Lords at laſt fully Agreed all Things in Diſpute. So that King <hi>James,</hi> having forfeited by his Male-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Regal Truſt of the Executive Power, both in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Heirs Lineal and Collateral, the ſame devolved back to the People; Who might lawfully diſpoſe thereof by their Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives, according to their good Will and Pleaſure, for their future Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Peace, Benefit and Security.</p>
               <p>Which was a clear Aſſertion of the Peoples Right, a firm Evidence of a Contract broken, and a ſure Precedent to all Ages; when, after a moſt ſolemn Debate, the Eſtates of <hi>England</hi> declare, That the King having Abdicated the Government, and the Throne thereby Vacant, They think fit to fill it again with One who is not Immediate in the Line. Feſides that it will be a Caution to ſucceeding Kings, of what ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſequence a general Derogation from the Laws may be, when they find by this Inſtance the Exerciſe of the Kingly Office in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, not only with Reference to Themſelves, but precarious to their Family.</p>
               <p>And now, to fill up the Throne, what better Choice could the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention make, than of that very Prince, who with ſo great Expence,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58818:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>Hazard, conduct, Courage, and Generoſity, had ſo wonderfully Reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us both from Spiritual and Temporal Slavery, and Reſtored us to our ancient Laws, Religion, and Properties? In Prudence, Honour, and Gratitude, they could do no leſs than Pray him to Accept the Crown. Which was done accordingly.</p>
               <p>But the Nation's Gratitude and Generoſity went further, by making the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> King and Queen joyntly; it being a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Ineſtimable Value the People had for Her Highneſs, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Male-Adminiſtration of her Unhappy Father.</p>
               <p>Thus the Prince and Princeſs were made equal in Dignity, but not in Authority. For the Executive Power was ſolely lodged in the Prince. Firſt, becauſe two Perſons equal in Authority might differ in Opinion, and conſequently in Command; and it is evident, no Man can ſerve two Maſters. Secondly, becauſe a Man, by Nature, Education, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, is generally rendred more capable to Govern than a Woman. And, as the preſent State of <hi>Europe</hi> in general, ſo that of theſe Kingdoms in particular, required a vigorous and maſculine Adminiſtration. To recover what was loſt, to reſcue what was in danger, and rectify what was amiſs, could not be effected but by a Prince conſummate in the Art both of Peace and War. A Prince of known Honour, profound Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, undaunted Courage, and incomparable Merit; naturally inclined to be Juſt, Merciful, and Peaceable, and to do all publick Acts of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity for the good of Societies. Therefore, as the Convention thought fit out of Generoſity to declare the Prince and Princeſs King and Queen joyntly, that they might both equally ſhare the Glory of a Crown, and we the Happineſs of their Auſpicious Reign; ſo out of Prudence they lodged the Executive Power in the Prince only, as the fitteſt Perſon under Heaven to Govern in this difficult Juncture.</p>
               <p>During theſe Tranſactions the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> arrived from <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Landed at <hi>White-Hall</hi> on the 12th. of <hi>February;</hi> the welcome News whereof was received with all manner of Publick Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Joy.</p>
               <p>The next Day the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons Aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminiſter,</hi> preſented to the Prince and Princeſs their Declaration, by the Marqueſs of <hi>Hallifax</hi> Speaker to the Houſe of Lords. Which Declaration contained a Sum of the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes upon the Laws of the Kingdom and the Liberties of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Vindication of the Ancient Rights and Liberties of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by declaring his aſſumed Power Illegal, their Offer of the Crown to Their Highneſies, and the new Oaths to be taken, according to the late Reſolves of the Grand Convention.</p>
               <p>The Offer of the Crown, with the Settlement thereof, was thus expreſied; <hi>That</hi> William <hi>and</hi> Mary <hi>Prince and Princeſs of</hi> Orange, <hi>be, and be declared King and Queen of</hi> England, France, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions thereunto belonging; To hold the Crown and Royal Dig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity of the ſaid Kingdoms and Dominions to them the ſaid Prince and Princeſs, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Lives, and the Life of the Surviver of them; And that the ſole and full Exerciſe of the Regal Power be only in, and executed by the ſaid Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>in the Names of the ſaid Prince and Princeſs, during <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58818:39"/>their joynt Lives; and after their Deceaſes, the ſaid Crown and Royal Dignity of the ſaid Kingdoms and Dominions to be to the Heirs of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the ſaid Princeſs; and, for default of ſuch Iſſue, to the Princeſs</hi> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Denmark, <hi>and the Heirs of her Body; and, for default of ſuch Iſſue, to the Heirs of the Body of the ſaid Prince of</hi> Orange.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To which his Highneſs gave this Gracious Anſwer.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This is certainly the greateſt Proof of the Truſt you have in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s that can be given, which is the Thing that makes us Value it the more; and we thankfully Accept what you have Offered. And, as I had no other Intention in coming hither, than to preſerve your Religion, Laws, and Liberties; ſo you may be ſure, that I ſhall indeavour to ſupport them, and ſhall be willing to concur in any Thing that ſhall be for the Good of the Kingdom, and to do all that is in my power to advance the Welfare of the Glory of the Nation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Whereupon the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> were that very Day (being the 13th. of <hi>February,</hi> 1688/9.) Proclaimed at <hi>White-Hall</hi> and in the City, King and Queen of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Name of <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY;</hi> each Proclamation being Ecchoed with Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Acclamations of Joy by the Multitudes of People which crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Streets, Windows, and Balconies; and the Streets lined all the Way from <hi>Temple-Bar</hi> to the <hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> with four Regiments of the City Militia. The Night was concluded with Bonfires, Ringing of Bells, and all other Expreſſions of Duty and Affection to Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>KING WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN MARY,</hi> with hearty Wiſhes for Their long and happy Reign.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> 11th. Being appointed for their Coronation, Their Majeſties were accordingly Crowned that Day at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with great Pomp and Solemnity, by the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London;</hi> and the Day kept with great Ceremony in moſt of the chief Towns of <hi>England.</hi> The Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath was tendred by the Biſhop to the King and Queen, in theſe ſeveral Articles, Their Majeſties giving a diſtinct Anſwer to each of them.</p>
               <p>Biſhop. <hi>Will you ſolemnly Premiſe and Swear to Govern the People of this Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>and the Dominions thereto belonging, according to the Statutes agreed on in Parliament, and the Laws and Cuſtoms of the ſame?</hi> King and Queen. <hi>I ſolemnly promiſe ſo to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhop. <hi>Will you to your power cauſe Law and Juſtice in Mercy to be executed in all Your Judgments?</hi> King and Queen. <hi>I will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhop. <hi>Will You to the utmoſt of your power Maintain the Laws of God, the true Profeſſion of the Goſpel, and the Proteſtant Reformed Religion eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law? And will you Preſerve unto the Biſhops and Clergy of this Realm, and to the Churches committed to their Charge, all ſuch Rights and Priviledges as by Law do or ſhall appertain unto them, or any of them?</hi> King and Queen. <hi>All this I promiſe to do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this the <hi>King and Queen</hi> laying his and her Hand upon the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goſpels, ſaid, <hi>The Things which I have here before Promiſed, I will Perform and Keep. So help me God.</hi> Then the <hi>King and Queen</hi> kiſſed the Book.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Scotland</hi> the ſame Courſe was taken for Settling the Government there, by a Convention which met at <hi>Edenburg</hi> upon the
14th. of <hi>March,</hi> 
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:58818:39"/>according to the Direction of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (now King) and the Advice of ſeveral Lords and Gentlemen of <hi>Stotland</hi> then at <hi>London.</hi> Which Convention voted alſo King <hi>James by his Miſgovernment to have forfeited the Right to the Crown, and the Throne to be Vacant.</hi> For the filling up whereof, they conferred the Crown upon <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY,</hi> King and Queen of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and fetled the Succeſſion in the ſame manner as our Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had done; with a new Oath of Allegiance to Their Majeſties. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, on the 11th. of <hi>April</hi> 1689. being their Coronation-day at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> Their Majeſties were proclaimed at <hi>Edenburg</hi> King and Queen of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. of <hi>May</hi> next enſuing, being the Day appointed for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Reception of the Commiſſioners ſent up by the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> Sir <hi>James Montgomery,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Dalrymple</hi>) to Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Crown of that Kingdom to their Majeſties, and tender unto Them the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Coronation Oath; they accordingly met at the Council Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at Three a Clock in the Afternoon, and were from thence conducted by Sir <hi>Charles Cotterel</hi> Maſter of the Ceremonies, to the Banqueting-Houſe, being attended by moſt of the Nobility and Gentry of that Kingdom then reſiding here. The King and Queen went thither attended by many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality, the Sword being carried before them by the Lord <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droſſe.</hi> And, Their Majeſties being placed on the Throne under a rich Canopy, the Commiſſioners firſt preſented a Letter from the Eſtates to the King, then the Inſtrument of Government, after that a Paper containing the Grievances to be Redreſſed, and laſtly an Addreſs to his Majeſty, for turning the Meeting of the ſaid Eſtates into a Parliament. All which being Signed by his Grace the Duke of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> as Preſident of the Meeting, and Read to Their Majeſties, the King returned to the Commiſſioners the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When I Ingaged in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, I had particular Regard and Conſideration for</hi> Scotland; <hi>and therefore I did omit a Declaration in relation to That as well as to This Kingdom, which I intend to make good and effectual to them. I take it very kindly, that</hi> Scotland <hi>has expreſſed ſo much Confidence in and Affection to Me. They ſhall find Me willing to aſſiſt Them in every Thing that concerns the Weal and Intereſt of that Kingdom, by making what Laws ſhall be neceſſary for the Security of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Property, and Liberty, and to eaſe them of what may be juſtly Grievous to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This done, the Coronation Oath was tendered to Their Majeſties; which the Earl of <hi>Argile</hi> ſpoke word by word diſtinctly, and the King and Queen repeated it after him, holding their right Hands up, after the manner of taking Oaths in <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Oath was thus. <hi>We</hi> William <hi>and</hi> Mary, <hi>King and Queen of</hi> Scotland, <hi>faithfully Promiſe and Swear by this our ſolemn Oath, in preſence of the Eternal God, That during the whole Courſe of our Life, we will ſerve the ſame Eternal God to the uttermoſt of our Power, according as he has requited in his moſt Holy Word revealed and contained in the New and Old Teſtament; and according to the ſame Word ſhall Maintain the true Religion of Chriſt Jeſus, the Preaching of his Holy Word, and the due and right Miniſtration of the Sacraments now Received and Preached within the Realm of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and ſhall Aboliſh and Gainſtand all falſe Religion contrary to the ſame; and ſhall Rule the People com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our Charge according to the Will und Command of God, revealed in his aforeſaid Word, and according to the laudable Laws and Conſtitutions received in this Realm, no ways rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnant to the ſaid Word of the Eternal God; and ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to the utmoſt of our Power to the Kirk of God and whole Chriſtian People true
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58818:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>and perfect Peace in all time coming. That we ſhall preſerve and keep inviolated the Rights and Rents, with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt Priviledges of the Crown of</hi> Scotland; <hi>neither ſhall We Transfer, nor Alienate the ſame. That We ſhall forbid and repreſs in all Eſtates and Degrees Reiſ Oppreſſion, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> kind of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rong; and We ſhall command and procure that Juſtice and Equity in all Judgments be keeped to all Perſons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, as the Lord and Father of Mercies ſhall be merciful to us. That We ſhall be careful to Root out all Hereticks and Enemies to the true Worſhip of God, that ſhall be Convilled by the true Kirk of God of the aforeſaid Crimes, out of Our Lands and Empire of</hi> Scotland. <hi>And We ſaithfully Affirm the Things above-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by Our Solemn Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, at the Repeating that Clauſe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Oath which relates to the Root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Hereticks, the King Daclared, <hi>That he did not mean by theſe Words, that he was under any Obligation to become a Perſecutor.</hi> To which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, Authorized thereto by the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> made Anſwer, <hi>That neither the Meaning of the Oath, nor the Law of</hi> Scotland, <hi>did imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> it.</hi> Then the King replied, <hi>That he took the Oath in that ſenſe,</hi> and called for Witneſſes the Commſſioners and others preſent. And then both Their Majeſties ſigned the ſaid Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onation Oath. After which the Commiſſioners, and ſeveral of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nobility, kiſſed Their Majeſties Hands.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and <hi>MARY,</hi> Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> were by the Grace and Providence of God, for the good of theſe Kingdoms, made King and Queen of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> in Oppoſition to all Malecontents. A Race of Men content in no Condition, who in a State of Slavery are eager for Liberty, and when ſet at Liberty are again for Slavery. Theſe are the Tools hitherto made uſe of by King <hi>Lewis,</hi> to diſtract theſe Kingdoms (under the ſpecious Pretence of Reſtoring the late King <hi>James</hi> to the Throne) by their dark Plotting here againſt the Government, and their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Rebellion in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Where the Duke of <hi>Gourdon,</hi> Governour of <hi>Edenburg</hi> Caſtle, held it out for King <hi>James</hi> till the 13th. of <hi>June;</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Dundee,</hi> at the Head of an Army of Rebels, was killed in a Field-fight on the <hi>1ſt.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> From which time the Rebels there never thrived, but were glad at laſt to imbrace Their Majeſties moſt Gracious Pardon.</p>
               <p>The greateſt Difficulty was to Reduce <hi>Ireland,</hi> then in the hands of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, fortifyed with a great Army, aſſiſted by the <hi>French</hi> King, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced by the late King <hi>James.</hi> Who look'd upon <hi>ireland</hi> as a Back-door for him to return into <hi>England,</hi> with a Crucifix in one hand, and a Sword in the other. <hi>Ireland.</hi> that had been ſo often Conquered by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> was now to Conquer <hi>England;</hi> and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> did not by their <hi>Shouls</hi> conſider, whether it was for King <hi>James</hi> or King <hi>Lewis.</hi> They were pleaſed with the Notion of an Infallible Conqueſt; and, before they had drawn the Sword, they fell forſooth dividing the Spoil amongſt themſelves. Incouraged by King <hi>James</hi>'s Preſence, now come from <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Dublin</hi> about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Year 89, nothing was to ſtand before them, <hi>London-Derry,</hi> in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was the only place of Note that ſtood out for Their Majeſties. The <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> being reſolved to reduce it by Fire, Sword, and Famine, ſat before it; and brought it to that extremity, that good part of the Town was by <hi>French</hi> Bombs reduced into Aſhes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 5000 of the Inhabitants died for want of Proviſions. Yet, under theſe diſmal Circumſtances, the Town held out, under the Conduct of that Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58818:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>Clergy-Man the Reverend Dr. <hi>Walker,</hi> till it was Relieved by Major General <hi>Kirk July</hi> 31. 1689. What happened ſince all the World knows. The famous Battle at the River <hi>Boyne,</hi> fought the next Year after, is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Monument of King <hi>William</hi>'s incomparable Valour and Conduct, and of God's wonderful Providence over his Royal Perſon. By this Battle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was bleſſed with a glorious Victory, he drove King <hi>James</hi> with full ſpeed out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> he got poſſeſſion of the Capital City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Drogheda, Wexford, Waterford,</hi> and other places of leſs note; ſo that two parts in three of <hi>Ireland</hi> were in a manner Reduced in one Campaign. Afterwards <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Kingſale</hi> were happily Recovered by the Earl of <hi>Marl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough.</hi> And this Years Expedition under the Chief Conduct of that Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant, Fortunate, Wiſe, and Skilful General, the Baron <hi>de G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>okle,</hi> will be eternally famous for Compleating ſo Succeſsfully the Reduction of that Kingdom, by the Surrender of <hi>Ballymore,</hi> the Taking of <hi>Athlone</hi> by Storm, the great Victory at <hi>Agh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im,</hi> the ſurrender of <hi>Galloway</hi> and <hi>Sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and at laſt that of <hi>Limerick,</hi> a Place lookt upon as alm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Impregnable. So that we ſee now a Kingdom, which (beſides its own Strength) has been power-fully Aſſiſted by the <hi>French,</hi> and Countenanced by the late King <hi>James,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely Reduced to their Majeſties Obedience, at the end of two Campaigns. Which I hope may convince the moſt Obſtinate, eſpecially after a long Chain of unaccountable and unlookt for Providences, that this great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution is not only by the Will or Permiſſion of Almighty God, but that it is his own Work; who is free to diſpoſe of Crowns and Kingdoms, to ſhew Mercy and Judgment upon whom he pleaſes. And, if it be ſo, I cannot imagine how Intailed Kings (good or bad) can be more <hi>de J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Divino</hi> than our Great King <hi>William.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee King <hi>James</hi> II. an Unfortunate Prince, who might have been a moſt glorious Monarch, fal'n (with the Loſs of three Crowns) a Sacrifice to Prieſts and Jeſuits; and fain to creep under the Shelter of a King, who is not like to hold out long himſelf, if he muſt give an Account to God and Men of the abominable Tranſactions of his Reign. Thus is the Curſe of King <hi>James</hi> I. come upon King <hi>James</hi> II, which he ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pronounced upon any of his Poſterity that ſhould forſake the Church of <hi>England</hi> to imbrace that of <hi>Rome.</hi> And yet, had it been poſſible for him to keep within ſome reaſonable Bounds, and his Religion to himſelf, without trampling (as he did) upon the Laws, he might have hitherto ſat upon the Throne; and 'tis like the Nation, upon his account, would have been very Indulgent to the Roman Catholick Party. But he would never be adviſed to Moderation, and no Counſellors were welcome to him but ſuch as prompted him to Violence. The Iſſue whereof proved accordingly; <hi>All Covet, all Loſe.</hi> And 'tis obſervable, that, as great as King <hi>James</hi> was with King <hi>Lewis,</hi> yet the Court of <hi>France</hi> was allowed openly to declare his Errors to the World, and paſſed this Verdict upon him, <hi>That his whole Conduct had been very little Judicious.</hi> The Emperor on the other ſide could not forbear in his Letter to him dated <hi>April</hi> 9. 1689. amongſt his tender condoling Expreſſions, to remind him of ſome of <hi>his falſe Politicks.</hi> I am heartily ſorry for his Fate; but it is better ſo than to ſee three Kingdoms periſh. I remember one of his Expreſſions at his firſt coming to the Crown, <hi>that he would carry the Glory of</hi> England <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58818:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>all his Predeceſſors,</hi> which he has made good in ſome ſenſe. For, by his I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>legal and Arbitrary Methods, he has given us an Opportunity, after ſome Years of tireſom Paſſive Obedience, of ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wing to the World how loth we are to part with our Laws, Religion, and Liberties, and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of that uneaſy double Yoak, which other Nations groan under. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, far from deſerving the Cenſure of Mankind, we are applauded for it all the World over, by all diſintereſted, ſenſible, and rational Men. And, after two weak, eſſeminate, and inglorious Reigns, which had ſunk the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tation and Honour of this Nation, and made us all over <hi>Europe</hi> an Object of Scorn and Contempt, we have by this way of Repriſal recovered our Credit, and are now able by the Grace of God to lift up our Heads beyond their expectation.</p>
               <p>But, if you inquire into the Cauſes of this ſudden Change, a Nameleſs Author will bring you in a parcel of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> a ſort of hair-brain'd States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and yet bred up in a Cloyſter; who being unacquainted both with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Temper and Conſtitution, hoped to have carried two ſuch things as Popery and Arbitrary Power, both at once, upon ſo Jealous a Nation as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> is, which hates them above any other People in the World. And yet theſe are the Men that bore the greateſt ſway in King <hi>James</hi>'s Counſels. I confeſs, ſays he, a Nation of leſs Senſe might have been Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon; of leſs bravery and Valour, might have been Frighted; of a more ſervile Temper, might have neglected its Liberties, till it had been too late to have recovered them.</p>
               <p>Theſe Jeſuits Manage with the Diſſenters of one ſide, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> Party on the other, ſhews how ſhallow-brain'd they were. One would think the cruel Slaughter they had cauſed to be made by the Courſe of Juſtice of the poor Wretches that were taken after the Defeat of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi>'s Army near <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> ſhould have made them for ever deſpair of gaining any Credit with the Diſſenters, who rarely forgive, but never forget any ill Treatment. But on the contrary they had ſo little ſenſe as to build all their hopes on them, for having procured unto them a Liberty of Conſcience, Arbitrarily and Illegally granted, and conſequently Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable at the Will of the Granter. Thus theſe little <hi>Politico</hi>'s rely'd upon the Diſſenters Gratitude and pretended Inſenſibility, as if for an uncertain Liberty of Conſcience they would have ſold themſelves to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Slavery. On the other ſide, if we look upon their Carriage towards the Church of <hi>England</hi> Party, it will appear how little they were to be truſted by the whole Proteſtant Party. Firſt they purſued both Clergy and Laity with the utmoſt obloquy, hatred, oppreſſion and contempt. But when they ſound the <hi>Dutch</hi> Storm coming upon them, who but the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Men? Then the Biſhops were preſently ſent for, and all Places, Preſſes, and flying Papers fill'd with the Encomiums of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; who but few days before were repreſented as Malecontents, if not Rebels and Traytors, for Oppoſing the King's Diſpenſing Power and the Eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſtical Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>To Compleat their Folly and Madneſs, they perſwaded King <hi>James</hi> to Throw up the Government, and Retire into <hi>France.</hi> For they pretended we ſhould never be able to agree amongſt our ſelves, but would in a ſhort time be forced to recall him, and fairly yield to his Will and Pleaſure, or be compell'd to it by the Succours he might gain in <hi>France.</hi> Had <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58818:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>France</hi> been now in Peace, there might have been (ſays my Author) ſome Colour for this. But, when all <hi>Europe</hi> was under a Neceſſity to Unite againſt him for its own Preſervation, then to perſwade King <hi>James</hi> to deſert his Throne, and fly to <hi>France</hi> for Succour, this was ſo ſilly a Project, that there ſeems to have been ſomething of a Divine Infatuation in it. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> might have taught them <hi>cuncta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> who would not ſtir from <hi>Holland,</hi> till he ſaw <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> irrevocably Ingaged in War, as it happened by the Siege of <hi>Philips<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, all Things conſidered, either King <hi>James</hi> ſhould have ſtaid here, and made as good Terms as he could with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and his own Subjects. Or, if he would Abandon his Kingdoms, he ought to have deſpaired of any Reſtitution, and betaken himſelf to a private Life, as Queen <hi>Chriſtina</hi> did.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="advice">
            <head>THE POSTSCRIPT, By Way of Advice to the <hi>Jacobite</hi> Party.</head>
            <p>NOw <hi>Ireland</hi> is Reduced, and the <hi>Scotch</hi> Rebellions Suppreſſed, 'tis high Time for you, Gentlemen, to Capitulate. Providence has declared it ſelf againſt you; your Idol the <hi>French</hi> King's Oracles are ceaſed, and he has now at laſt moſt baſely left you in the lurch. In ſhort, there is no hopes or proſpect of Relief. You have done enough in <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and more than enough, for King <hi>James.</hi> You have out-done not only your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, but Primitive Chriſtianity it ſelf, in your fond Scruple of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience about the Oaths; and have evidenced to the World, how Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is to ſerve two Maſters. Only ſome of you went too far, and made ſhift for King <hi>James</hi>'s Service to ſwear themſelves true Subjects to King <hi>William,</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> too. To bring back King <hi>James</hi> with Popery. Triumphant, you have ſtuck at nothing; and have over come even Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf, by putting your ſelves under a King's Protection, who ever was an Enemy to this Crown and Nation I mean the great King <hi>Lewis,</hi> whoſe Quarrel you eſpouſed, whoſe Greatneſs you admired, whoſe Succeſſes you applauded too. A <hi>Moſt Chriſtian</hi> King, in League with <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> (now become your Confederates) againſt the Prefeſſors of the Name of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> A Prince who has a great Account to give to God and Men of his infinite Extortions, Rapines, Violences, Breach of Faith, Bloodſhed, and Perſecutions. With this great Tyrant, Uſurper, and Perſecutor, you have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to Overthrow the preſent Government, by dark Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, by bold Speeches and virulent Libels, by filling the Nation with Fears and Jealouſies. But that which I chiefly admire you for, is your Withſtanding all Temptations of Plenty, Eaſe, and Liberty, to become mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Slaves, even for Conſcience ſake. Your being proof againſt the ſtrongeſt Arguments of the beſt Pens of the Nation, which could never make the leaſt Impreſſion upon you. To which add your fervent (but ineffectual) Prayers and Supplications to God, for a Bleſſing upon your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>al Indeavours; and, if they have not proſpered, 'tis not your Fault. <pb n="80" facs="tcp:58818:42"/>In a Word, ſo tranſcendent and meritorious has been your Loyalty to the late King <hi>James,</hi> that no Age can parallel it. So great, that, like <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Wiſdom, never was the like before it, nor I hope will ever be after. So deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, that it made you willing to Sacrifice your Lives and Fortunes, your Liberty, Nation, Poſterity, and ſome of you their Religion, only to have the Satisfaction to ſing <hi>Allelujah</hi> at the Return of King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this was well enough, according to your Principles, as long as <hi>Limerick</hi> held out. But now the Caſe is altered, and it is time to Deſiſt. King <hi>James</hi> his Back-door is ſhut; and the <hi>Great King</hi> having now withdrawn his powerful Arm, tis in vain for you to hold out. I adviſe you therefore to Surrender, while it is time, to Their Majeſties Mercy; and to become Their true and faithful Subjects, under whoſe eaſy Scepter you may live happily.</p>
            <p>Thus you will be no more lookt upon as you have been hitherto, with Pity, Scorn, and Indignation. With Pity, as being Miſguided by an erroneous Principle. With Score, for the greateſt Infatuation that Men were ever guilty of, to ſtand for Slavery when you are Free, as you wiſhed for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance when you were in Captivity. With Indignation, as being the Bane of the Government, under whoſe Protection you live.</p>
            <p>When all is done, you cannot but grant, that the King is none of thoſe frightful Princes that you took him to be, from the Lords Speech without Doors, and others of his Kidney. Nor have we felt in the ſpace of almoſt three Years any of thoſe direful Influences of his Reign, which thoſe unlucky Fortune-tellers did once threaten us with. He is a merciful King; You have experienced it. A Wiſe and Warlike Prince; <hi>France</hi> it ſelf does own it. So great is his Fame and Intereſt abroad, that He is in a manner the Oracle of moſt Chriſtian Princes, and the moſt likely King we have had ſince <hi>Henry</hi> V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to make this Nation both Glorious and Happy. As he is a Pattern for Princes in point of Government, ſo in the Courſe of a Chriſtian Life, he is a Pattern for Subjects; being both Good and Great, and therefore the fitteſt Monarch to make this Nation ſo. After ſo many eſſeminate and inglorious Reigns, what greater Bleſſing could Heavens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon us than a Prince ſo well qualified to Reign in theſe Kingdoms? This is not all. It has pleaſed God to redouble our Happineſs, by ſetting over us, in Conjunction with his Majeſty, a Queen who is the Glory of her Sex, and a Princeſs alone worthy of ſo great a Prince. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be Unanimous, and ſay with one Voice,</p>
            <closer>God Save and Proſper King William and Queen Mary.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>An Advertiſement of ſome Books ſold by <hi>Samuel Clement</hi> at the <hi>Lute</hi> in <hi>Paul's-Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. GOd's Revenge againſt Murther and Adultery, expreſſed in Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeveral Tragical Hiſtories. The Third Edition. By <hi>Thomas Wright,</hi> M. A. of St. <hi>Peters</hi> College in <hi>Cambr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Engliſh Grammar, ſetting ſorth the Grounds of the Engliſh Tongue. By <hi>Guy Miege.</hi> Gent. The Second Edition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Delightful Hiſtory of <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> the moſt Renowned Baron of <hi>Mancha.</hi> With the Comical Humours of <hi>Sancho Panca.</hi> The Second Edition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58818:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
